<chapter id="config-prefs">

      <title>Advanced Configuration</title>
      <para>
        Perhaps your mail server has changed names.  Perhaps you've
        grown tired of a certain layout for your appointments.
        Whatever the reason, you want to change your
        Evolution settings.  This chapter
        will tell you how to do just that.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can reach the Evolution settings window 
        by choosing <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, no matter
        where you are in Evolution. On the left half of the settings
        window is a column, similar to the Evolution shortcut bar,
        which lets you choose which portion of Evolution to
        customize. The right half of the window is where you'll make
        your actual changes.
      </para>


      <!-- ==============Figure===================== -->
      <figure id="config-prefs-mail-fig">
	<title>Changing Mail Settings</title>
	<screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Changing Mail Settings</screeninfo>
	  <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/config-mail" format="PNG" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/>
	    </imageobject></mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>
      <!-- ==============End of Figure================-->

  <para>
    There are eight items you can customize. From top to bottom, they
    are:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><guiicon>Mail Accounts</guiicon></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
             Here, add or change information about your email
             accounts: the servers to which you connect, the way you
             download mail, your password authentication mode, and so
             forth. This is the most complex item in the list, and is
             covered in <xref linkend="config-prefs-mail-identity"/>.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><guiicon>Folder Settings</guiicon></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
             Here, you can choose the default folders for various
             components of Evolution, the folders that will be cached
             locally when you go to offline mode, and the folders that
             Evolution will use when it is searching for
             autocompletion information as you address a mail.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><guiicon>Mail Preferences</guiicon></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
             These are overall mail reading preferences: display
             settings, notification options, security, and so
            forth. Settings that vary per-account are in the Mail
            Accounts tool, described in <xref
            linkend="config-prefs-mail-identity"/>, but most of the
            mail settings are here.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><guiicon>Composer Preferences</guiicon></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
             Settings for the way that you use the mail composer:
             shortcuts, signatures, spelling, and so forth. One fun
             feature here is the ability to substitute graphical
             smiley-faces for "emoticons" such as :) that many people
             use in email. This tool is covered in <xref
             linkend="config-prefs-mail-composer"/>.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><guiicon>Calendar and Tasks</guiicon></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
             Here, you can set the way the calendar behaves, including
             your time zone and the length of your work-week.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><guiicon>Exchange Delegation</guiicon></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
            This item will only appear if you have Evolution Connector
            for Microsoft Exchange installed. It will allow you to
            choose who has access to your Exchange account. This
            feature is covered in <xref linkend="exchange-delegate" />.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term><guiicon>Directory Servers</guiicon></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
             This item allows you to enter account information for
            connecting to remote directory (LDAP) servers.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
	<term><guiicon>Out of Office</guiicon></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
            This item will only appear if you have Evolution Connector
            for Microsoft Exchange installed. It allows you to create
            and remove automatic "vacation" messages.  For
            information about how to use this feature, read <xref
            linkend="exchange-out-of-office" />.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </para>

   <sect1 id="config-prefs-mail-identity">
      <title>Working with Mail Accounts</title> 
      <para>
         Novell Evolution allows you to
         maintain multiple accounts, or identities.  This is useful
         want to keep personal and professional email separate, or if
         you wear several hats at work. When you are writing an email
         message, you can which account to use by selecting from the
         drop-down list next to the <guilabel>From</guilabel> entry in
         the message composer.
       </para>

       <para>
         Clicking <guilabel>Send/Receive</guilabel> will refresh any
         IMAP, <filename>mh</filename>, or
         <filename>mbox</filename> listings
         and check and download mail from all POP servers.  In other
         words, <guilabel>Send/Receive</guilabel> gets your mail, no
         matter how many sources you have, or what types they are.  If
         you don't want to check mail for a given account, select it
         in the <guilabel>Mail Accounts</guilabel> tab and click the
         <guilabel>Disable</guilabel> button.
       </para>
       
      <para>
         To add a new account, simply click <guilabel>Add</guilabel>
         to open the mail configuration assistant. To alter an
         existing identity, select it in the
         <interface>Preferences</interface> window, and then click
         <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> to open the account editor
         dialog.
      </para>

     <para>
         The account editor dialog has six sections:
          <variablelist>

	  <varlistentry> 
	    <term><guilabel>Identity</guilabel></term>
           <listitem>
	    <para>
              Here, enter the name,
              email address, and other identifying information for the
              account. You may also choose a default signature to
              insert into messages sent from this account.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry> 
	    <term><guilabel>Receiving Mail</guilabel></term>
           <listitem>
	    <para>
             Here, select the way you will be getting mail: you may
             download mail from a server (<glossterm
             linkend="pop">POP</glossterm>), read and keep it on the
             server (Microsoft Exchange or <glossterm
             linkend="imap">IMAP</glossterm>), or read it from files
             that already exist on your desktop computer.  If you use
             a server, it may permit or require you to use a Secure
             Socket Layer (SSL) connection.  To turn SSL connections
             on, just click the <guilabel>Use Secure Connection
             (SSL)</guilabel> button.

<note id="config-arbitrary-port">
<title>Specifying Port Numbers</title>
<para>
Your system administrator may ask you to connect to a specific port on
a mail server. To specify which port you use, just type a colon and
the port number after the server name. For example, to connect to port
143 on the server smtp.omniport.com, you would enter
as
<userinput>
smtp.omniport.com:143
</userinput> as the server name.
</para>
</note>

	  </para>
	  </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry> 
	    <term><guilabel>Receiving Options</guilabel></term>
           <listitem>
	    <para>
              Here, decide whether you'd like to check for mail
              automatically and how often, as well as other message
              retrieval options.

              <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                   <term>If you chose POP:</term>
                   <listitem>
                     <para>
                   <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem>
			    <para><guilabel>Checking for new mail:</guilabel> If you would
	                     like Evolution
	                     to check for new mail automatically,
	                     check the box and select a frequency in
	                     minutes.
                           </para>
			  </listitem>

			  <listitem>
			    <para>
                             <guilabel>Leave messages on server:</guilabel> If you'd like to store
	                      copies of your mail on the server, check
	                      this option.
                           </para>
			  </listitem>
		
			
                           <listitem>
                             <para><guilabel>Disable support for all
                             POP3 extensions:</guilabel> Some email
                             servers refuse to work with the extended
                             POP3 command set; select this item to
                             have Evolution use a more limited set of
                             interactions with the server. If your
                             server periodically drops your
                             connection, this option may help.
                           </para>
			  </listitem>
	               </itemizedlist>
                      </para>
		    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry> 

                <varlistentry>
                   <term>If you chose Microsoft Exchange:</term>
                   <listitem>
                     <para>

	    <itemizedlist> <listitem>
		<para><guilabel>Checking for new mail</guilabel>: If you would like
                Evolution to check for new mail automatically, check
                the box and select a frequency in minutes.
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
                  <guilabel>Global Catalog server name</guilabel>: enter the name of your
                  Global Catalog server to create a folder for your
                  organization's Global Address List.
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><guilabel>Limit number of Responses</guilabel>: Select a maximum number
		of results for an address search. Lowering the maximum
		number the load on your system and on your
                network. Most servers will not send more than 1000
                results, regardless of the value you select here.
		  </para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><guilabel>Mailbox Name</guilabel>: Enter your mailbox name.
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
                <guilabel>OWA Path</guilabel>: Enter the path used with Outlook Web Access on your server.
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
                  <guilabel>Public Folder Server</guilabel>: Enter the name of your public
                  folder server, if it differs from your Exchange server.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
                  <guilabel>Apply Filters to new messages in Inbox on this
                  server</guilabel>: check this box if you wish to apply filters
                  to this account.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>                       
                     </para>
                   </listitem>
                  </varlistentry> 

                <varlistentry>
                   <term>If you chose IMAP:</term>
                   <listitem>
                     <para>
                      
         <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><guilabel>Checking for new mail</guilabel>: If you would like
	    Evolution to check for new mail
	    automatically, check the box and select a frequency in
	    minutes.  
            </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>If you want Evolution
	    to check for new messages in <emphasis>all</emphasis> your
	    IMAP folders, make sure the <guilabel>Check for new
	    messages in all folders</guilabel> box is selected.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><guilabel>Show only subscribed folders</guilabel>: Check this box if you
	    have more folders in your IMAP view than you want to
	    read.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              <guilabel>Override server-supplied namespace</guilabel>: If you like, enter a
              specific directory where your server stores mail for
              you.  Typical values are "mail" and "Mail."  For more
              information about how to use IMAP mail, see <xref
              linkend="usage-mail-subscriptions"/>.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><guilabel>Apply filters to new messages in INBOX on this
	    server</guilabel>: If you'd like your filters to work on this
            account, check this box.
          </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
                     </para>
                   </listitem>
                  </varlistentry> 

             
                  </variablelist>  
     </para>
	  </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry> 
	    <term><guilabel>Sending Mail</guilabel></term>
           <listitem>
	    <para>
              In this section, you will choose and configure a method
              for sending mail.  You may choose <glossterm
              linkend="smtp">SMTP</glossterm>, Microsoft Exchange (if
              you have installed the Evolution Connector for Microsoft
              Exchange) or <glossterm
              linkend="sendmail">sendmail</glossterm>.
             </para>
             <para>
               If you choose Exchange or Sendmail, you're done with
               this tab. SMTP offers you a choice of hostname,
               connection security level, and authentication type,
               which you will recognize as similar to those for
               IMAP and POP servers in the <guilabel>Receiving
               Mail</guilabel> tab.
             </para>
	  </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry> 
	    <term><guilabel>Defaults</guilabel></term>
           <listitem>
	    <para>
              Here, you can decide where this account will store the
              messages that it has sent, and the messages that you
              save as drafts. If you wish to revert to the "factory"
              settings, click the <guilabel>Restore
            Defaults</guilabel> button.
            </para>
            <para>
              If you wish to send someone a copy of every message from
              this account, check the box labeled <guilabel>Always
              carbon-copy (Cc) to:</guilabel> or <guilabel>Always
              blind carbon-copy (Bcc) to:</guilabel>, and enter one or
              more addresses.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry> 
	    <term><guilabel>Security</guilabel></term>
           <listitem>
	    <para>
              In this section, you will set the security options for
              this account. If you use encryption, enter your PGP
              key id (see <xref linkend="encryption"/> for more
              information) and select among the four options below to
            determine key and signature handling.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </para>
    </sect1>
  
    <sect1 id="config-prefs-folders">
      <title>Folder Settings</title>
      <para>
        There are three sets of folder options. In the first,
        <guilabel>Default Folders</guilabel>, select which folders will be
        your usual mail, contacts, calendar, and tasks
        folders. When you save a contact or appointment attached to an
        email, it will be stored in your default contact or calendar
        folder.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <guilabel>Offline Folders</guilabel> are the ones that
        will be cached when you activate the <guilabel>Go
        Offline</guilabel> feature. 
      </para>
      <para>
        Select one or more folders of contacts for your
        <guilabel>Autocompletion Folders</guilabel>. When you type a
        few letters into the message composer address fields,
        Evolution will look for matches in the folders you choose here.
      </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="config-prefs-mail">
      <title>Mail Preferences</title>
      <para>
        The <guilabel>Mail Options</guilabel> tool lets you choose how
        to display citations, how long to wait before marking a
        message as read, and other mail display settings. There are
        three categories of settings: General, HTML Mail, and
        Colors.
      </para>
      <para>
        For information on individual email account settings, see <xref
        linkend="config-prefs-mail-identity" />.
      </para>

      <para>
        In the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab, your options are:
     <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
         <term><guilabel>Message Fonts</guilabel></term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             Normally, Evolution will use the same fonts as other
             GNOME applications. To choose different fonts, uncheck
             the box <guilabel>Use the same fonts as other
           applications</guilabel> and select one font for standard typefaces and 
           a second for monospace, or terminal, display.
           </para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
         <term><guilabel>Message Display</guilabel></term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             These three settings handle the way messages appear to
             you. 
             <variablelist>
               <varlistentry>
                 <term><guilabel>Mark Messages as Read...</guilabel></term>
                 <listitem>
                   <para> 
                   Normally, Evolution will mark a message as read as soon
                   as it is displayed. If you prefer, you may set this to
                   happen only after a delay, or disable it entirely and
                   mark messages as read only when you choose to do so.
                 </para>
                 </listitem>
               </varlistentry>
           
               <varlistentry>
                 <term><guilabel>Default Character Encoding</guilabel></term>
                 <listitem>
                   <para>
                     This setting allows you to select character
                     interpretation sets so that Evolution can display
                     different alphabets.  If you are not sure, pick
                     Unicode (UTF-8), which will work for a large
                     number of languages and character sets.
                   </para>
                 </listitem>
               </varlistentry>
           
               <varlistentry>
                 <term><guilabel>Highlight Quotations</guilabel></term>
                 <listitem>
                   <para>
                     Choose a color to highlight quotations from other
                     messages.
                   </para>
                 </listitem>
               </varlistentry>
             </variablelist>
           </para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       
       <varlistentry>
         <term><guilabel>Deleting Mail</guilabel></term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             Here, choose whether to delete messages automatically
             when quitting Evolution, and whether you wish to
             explicitly confirm the final deletion of messages.
           </para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
           
       <varlistentry>
         <term><guilabel>New Mail Notification</guilabel></term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
              Evolution can alert you to the arrival of new mail with
             a beep or by playing a sound file. Choose your alert
             noise, or select none, as you wish.
           </para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
   </para>
   <para>
     The options in the <guilabel>HTML Mail</guilabel> tab are:
   <variablelist>
    
       <varlistentry>
         <term><guilabel>Loading Image</guilabel></term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             You can embed a image in an email and have it load only
             when the message arrives. However, spammers can use image loading
             patterns to confirm "live" addresses and invade your
             privacy. You may elect never to load images
             automatically, to load images only if the sender is in
             your contacts, or always load images.
           </para>
           <para>
             If you have chosen not to load images automatically, you
             can choose to see the images in one message at a time by selecting <menuchoice>
             <guimenu>View</guimenu><guisubmenu>Message Display</guisubmenu>
             <guimenuitem>Load Images</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
           </para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
         <term><guilabel>Show animated images</guilabel></term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             Turn animation on or off here.
           </para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
         <term><guilabel>Prompt when sending HTML messages to contacts that don't want them</guilabel></term>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             Some people do not like HTML mail, and you can set
             Evolution to warn you. This warning will appear only
             when you send HTML mail to people in your contacts 
             who are listed as disliking HTML.
           </para>
         </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
   </para>
   <para>
     The <guilabel>Colors</guilabel> tab lets you select different
   color labels for individual messages. You can return to the default
   settings by clicking the <guilabel>Restore Defaults</guilabel>
   button.
 </para>
</sect1>


    <sect1 id="config-prefs-mail-composer">
      <title>Composer Preferences</title>
      <para>
        There are three  tabs of settings you can change for the
        message composer. The <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab covers shortcuts and
        assorted behavior, and the other two control signatures and
        spell checking.  In the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab, you can set:

         <variablelist>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Default Behavior</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
                 Choose how you will normally forward and reply
                 messages, what character set they will use, whether
                 they will be in HTML, and whether that HTML can
                 contain smiley face images.
               </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>


	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Alerts</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
                 There are two optional alerts here:
                 <variablelist>
	         <varlistentry>
		    <term><guilabel>Prompt when sending messages with an empty subject line</guilabel></term>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>
			 The composer will warn you if you try to send a
			 message without a subject.
		       </para>
		    </listitem>
		  </varlistentry>

		  <varlistentry>
		    <term><guilabel>Prompt when sending messages with only Bcc recipients defined</guilabel></term>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>
			 The composer will warn you if you try to send a
			 message that has only <guilabel>Bcc</guilabel>
			 recipients. This is important because some mail
			 servers will fail to honor blind carbon copy if you
			 do not have at least one recipient that is visible to
			 all readers.
		       </para>
		    </listitem>
		  </varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>
               </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>

     <para>
         The signature editor allows you to create several different
         signatures in plain text or in HTML, and to specify which of
         them will be added to emails you create in the message
         composer.  If you prefer to use an alternate signature or
         none at all, you can select it from the mail composer itself.
    </para>
    <para>
       In the spell-checking tool, you can set spelling options,
       including the language or languages you will use. Note that you
       must install the gnome-spell package, available through Red
       Carpet, for spell-checking to be available in
       Evolution. Alternate dictionaries are also available through
       Red Carpet and are detected automatically if you have installed
       them.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can check the spelling of messages by selecting
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Spell Check
      Document</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.  Alternately, in the
      Evolution main window select
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu><guisubmenu>Settings</guisubmenu></menuchoice>,
      click on the <guiicon>Composer preferences</guiicon> icon, then
      select the <guilabel>Spell Checking</guilabel> tab and check the
      <guilabel>Check spelling while I type</guilabel> box, and
      choose a color for your misspelled words.
  </para>
</sect1>

<!-- NOT FOR 1.0, see usage-mail.sgml
      <sect1 id="config-prefs-news">          
          <title>News Servers</title>
          <para>
            Newsgroups are so much like mailing lists that there's no
            reason not to keep them right next to your mail.  When you
            first select the <guilabel>News Servers</guilabel> tab,
            you will see a blank box with the three familiar buttons
            on the right: <guilabel>Add</guilabel>,
            <guilabel>Edit</guilabel>, and
            <guilabel>Delete</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para>
            Click <guilabel>Add</guilabel> to add a news server; you
            will be prompted for its name.  Enter the name, click
            <guilabel>OK</guilabel>, and you're done.  You can have
            as many news servers as you like, of course.  News servers
            will appear next to your IMAP servers in the
            <interface>folder bar</interface>.
          </para>
     </sect2>
  </sect1>
-->


    <sect1 id="config-prefs-cal">
       <title>Calendar and Tasks Settings</title>
       <para>
          The calendar configuration tool has two tabs
          <guilabel>General</guilabel> and
          <guilabel>Display</guilabel>, and is illustrated in <xref
          linkend="config-prefs-cal-fig"/>.

      <!-- ==============Figure===================== -->
      <figure id="config-prefs-cal-fig">
	<title>Calendar Preferences Dialog</title>
	<screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Calendar Configuration</screeninfo>
	  <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/config-cal" format="PNG" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/>
	    </imageobject></mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>
      <!-- ==============End of Figure================-->
        </para>

      <para>
        The General tab lets you set the
        following:
        <variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Time zone</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The city you're located in, to judge your time zone.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Time format</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>You may choose between twelve-hour (AM/PM) and
	      twenty-four hour time formats here by clicking the
	      appropriate radio button.
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Work Week</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		In the day and week views, Evolution displays all the
		hours in the range you select here, even if there are
		no appointments for those times.  You can
		still schedule an appointment outside of these hours,
		and if you do, the display will be extended to show
		it.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Week Starts</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>You can set weeks to start on Sunday or on Monday.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Day Begins</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Set the beginning of a normal workday. If you work odd
		hours, or want to make sure that your early-morning
		appointments are displayed, you may find this option useful.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Day Ends</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Set the end of a normal workday. If you work odd
		hours, or want to make sure that your evening
		appointments are displayed, you may find this option
		useful.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>


	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Alerts</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		If you'd like to be warned before you delete any
		appointment, or to have a reminder automatically
		appear for each event, select the check boxes here.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
       </para>

      <para>
	The Display tab lets you choose how
	your appointments and tasks will appear in your calendar.
      </para>
      <para>The display properties you can set are:

	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Time divisions</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
              <para>
                Sets the time increments shown as fine lines on the
                daily view in the calendar.
              </para>
            </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Show appointment end times in week and month views</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		If there is space, Evolution will show the end
		times in the week and month views for each
		appointment.
              </para>
            </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Compress weekends in month view</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		If checked, your weekends will be shown in one box,
		instead of one for each day in the month view.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Show week numbers in date navigator</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
              <para>
		This will show the week numbers next to the respective
		weeks in the calendar.
	      </para>
            </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	 <varlistentry>
	   <term><guilabel>Tasks due today</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
                Select the color for tasks due today.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Overdue tasks</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Choose the color for overdue tasks.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Hide Completed Tasks</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
                Check this box to have completed tasks hidden after a
                period of time measured in days, hours,
                or minutes.  If you leave the box unchecked,
                completed tasks will remain in your task list, marked
                as complete.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="config-prefs-contact">
    <title>Directory Servers</title>
    <para>
        Contacts settings are limited to the usage and
        configuration of directory servers (LDAP and
      Exchange). To learn how to set autocompletion options, see <xref
      linkend="config-prefs-folders" />.
      Other contacts controls are available in the contacts tool.
    </para>
      
      <para>
        To add a new group of contacts, either local or remote, do the following:
    </para>
	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              Go to the contacts tool by clicking the
              <guilabel>Contacts</guilabel> button.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              Right-click on the shortcut bar's list of contact groups,
              and select <guimenuitem>New Contact Group</guimenuitem>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Select a name and location for the contact group. The name
              is for display only. </para>

            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>
                Click <guilabel>Forward</guilabel>.  If the contact
              group is stored locally, then you don't have to
              provide any more information. Click
              <guilabel>OK</guilabel> and you are done.
              </para>
            </listitem>


	  <listitem>

	    <para>
              If you are creating an <glossterm
              linkend="ldap">LDAP</glossterm> server, enter the server information
            as requested by the assistant:
	    <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
                  <term><guilabel>Server name</guilabel></term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Internet address of the contact server you'll be using.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
                  <term><guilabel>Login Method</guilabel></term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Specify whether your login is anonymous, using
                      an email address, or a "distinguished name." If
                      the login is not anonymous, enter the email
                      address or distinguished name (DN) required by
                      the server.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
                  <term><guilabel>Port</guilabel></term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      The internet port
		      Evolution connects to
		      in order to access the LDAP database.  This is
		      normally 389.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term><guilabel>Use SSL/TLS</guilabel></term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
                      SSL and TLS are security mechanisms. If you
                      select <guilabel>Always</guilabel>, Evolution
                    will not connect unless
                    secure connections are available. The default value is
                    <guilabel>Whenever Possible</guilabel>, which uses
                    secure connections if they are available,
                    but does not cause failure if they are not.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>


		<varlistentry>
                  <term><guilabel>Search base</guilabel></term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      The <glossterm linkend="search-base">search
                    base</glossterm> is the starting point for a directory search. 
		      Contact your network administrator for information about
		      the correct settings.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
                  <term><guilabel>Search scope</guilabel></term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
                      The <glossterm linkend="search-scope">search
                    scope</glossterm> is the breadth of a given search. 
		    The  following options are available:
		      <variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
			  <term><guilabel>One</guilabel></term>
			  <listitem>
			    <para>
			      Searches the Search Base and one entry
			      below it.
			    </para>
			  </listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
			  <term><guilabel>Sub</guilabel></term>
			  <listitem>
			    <para>
			      Searches the Search Base and all entries
			      below it.
			    </para>
			  </listitem>
			</varlistentry>
                      </variablelist>
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><guilabel>Timeout (minutes)</guilabel></term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
                      This is the maximum time Evolution will attempt to
                      download data from the server before giving up.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>


                <varlistentry>
                  <term><guilabel>Download Limit</guilabel></term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Set the maximum number of results for a given
                      search. Most servers refuse to send more than
                      500, but you can set the number lower if you
                      want to shorten downloads for very broad
                      searches.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>


                <varlistentry>
                  <term><guilabel>Display name</guilabel></term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      This is the name you will use to label this
                      folder, and may be any name you choose.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

	      </variablelist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click <guilabel>Apply</guilabel>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
        <para>
          Editing a directory server account means changing that same
          information, although it is displayed in a slightly different order.
        </para>
    </sect1>


</chapter>