  <chapter id="config-sync">
     <title>Setting up your synchronization system</title> 
     <para>
        Synchronization presents you with two issues you'll need to
        address. First, your computer needs to recognize and access
       your handheld.  At this time, Novell Evolution only supports
       PalmOS devices like the Palm Pilot and the Handspring Visor.
       Secondly, you should decide what sort of synchronization
       behavior you want.
     </para>

    <para>
       If you haven't used a handheld device with your computer
       before, you'll need to run the GNOME Control
       Center by selecting
       <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice>,
       and make sure that <application>Pilot Link</application> is
       properly configured. You will need to make sure that you have
       read and write permissions on the device, which is normally
       /dev/pilot. If that does not work, check /dev/ttyS0 if you have
       a serial connection, or /dev/ttyUSB0 for a USB connection. You
       can do this by becoming root and running the command:
       <userinput>chmod 777 /dev/ttyUSB0</userinput>.
    </para>
    <para>
        Once your computer and your PalmOS device are talking happily
        to each other, select the <glossterm
        linkend="conduit">conduits</glossterm> you want under the
        <guilabel>Pilot Conduits</guilabel> section of the Control
        Center.  You may use conduits to synchronize data with several
        applications; the Novell Evolution
        conduits are labeled <guilabel>EAddress</guilabel>, for the
        contacts in your address book, <guilabel>ECalendar</guilabel>,
        for your calendar, and <guilabel>ETodo</guilabel>, for your
        task list.
    </para>
   <para>
      To enable a conduit, click the
        <guilabel>Enable</guilabel> to enable it, and click
        <guilabel>Settings</guilabel> to change what it will do when
        activated.  Your options may vary depending on the conduit,
        but typically they will be:

        <variablelist>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Disabled:</term>
            <listitem> 
               <para>
                  Do nothing.
               </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Synchronize:</term>
            <listitem> 
               <para>
                  Copy new data from the computer to the handheld, and
                  from the handheld to the computer.  Remove items
                  that were on both systems but have been deleted on
                  one.
               </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Copy From Pilot:</term>
            <listitem> 
               <para>
                  If there is any new data on the the handheld device,
                  copy it to the computer.
               </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Copy To Pilot:</term>
            <listitem> 
               <para>
                 Copy new data from the computer to the handheld. 
               </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Merge From Pilot:</term>
            <listitem> 
               <para>
                  Copy new data from the handheld to the computer, and
                  remove any information from the computer that has
                  been deleted on the handheld.
               </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Merge To Pilot:</term>
            <listitem> 
               <para>
                  Copy new data from the computer to the handheld, and
                  remove any information from the handheld that has
                  been deleted on the computer.
               </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
       </variablelist>
    </para>

    <para>
      Select the behavior you want for each conduit you choose to use.
      If you're not sure, go ahead and stick with
      <guilabel>Synchronize</guilabel>.  Then, put your handheld on
      its cradle and press the HotSync button.
    </para>
      <para> 
         <tip> 
	  <title>Data Loss Prevention</title> 
	  <para>
	    It's always a good idea to make a backup.  To do that,
	    make a copy of the <filename>evolution</filename>
	    directory inside your home directory.
          </para>
	</tip>
       </para>

    </chapter>




