 <chapter id="usage-exchange">
    <title>The Ximian Connector for Microsoft Exchange</title>
    <para>
    The Ximian Connector for Microsoft Exchange allows Ximian
    Evolution clients to access accounts on Microsoft Exchange 2000
    servers. It is available through Ximian Red Carpet in its own
    channel, but cannot be used without a license file.  The license
    file may be purchased from the Ximian online store at <ulink
    url="http://store.ximian.com">store.ximian.com</ulink>. Unlike the
    regular Ximian Evolution client, the Ximian Connector for
    Microsoft Exchange is proprietary software and source code is not
    available.
    </para>
   
  <warning id="licensing">
    <title>Requirements</title>
    <para>
      Ximian Connector works only with Exchange 2000, and requires
      that Outlook Web Access be enabled. Each user will need a
      valid Microsoft Exchange 2000 server account, including license.
  </para>
  </warning>

  <sect1 id="new-in-connector">
<title>What's New in Connector &appversion;</title>
  <para>
    Ximian Connector &appversion; has added the <guilabel>Out of
    Office</guilabel> feature and an automatic configuration tool for
    large Exchange deployments.
  </para>

  <para>
    Previous versions of Ximian Connector for Microsoft Exchange added
    support for the <guibutton>Flag for Followup</guibutton> feature,
    public folders, delegation, direct booking, and more. For
    information on setting up delegation, see <xref
  linkend="exchange-delegate" />.
  </para>

</sect1>

  <sect1 id="features">
    <title>Connector Features</title>
    <para>
      In addition to the features listed above, <application>Ximian
      Connector</application> supports the following basic 
      <application>Microsoft Exchange</application> features:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    General
	  </para>
	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Remote <application>Exchange</application> Information Store</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Allows you to access mail, address book (including
		  Global Address List folder), and calendars, and task
		  folders on an <application>Exchange
		  2000</application> server from
		  <application>Evolution</application>.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Palm synchronization</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Supported for Contacts and Calendars on Exchange.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	  </variablelist>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Mail
	  </para>
	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Viewing Mail in <application>Exchange</application>Folder</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para></para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Sending Email via Exchange Protocols</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  You may use the Microsoft Exchange mail transport
		  protocol to send email. Make sure that the address
		  you have entered as your email address is exactly
		  the one that the Exchange server has on file. This
		  may be "yourname@exchange-server.ximian.com" rather
		  than "yourname@ximian.com.a"
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	  </variablelist>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Calendar
	  </para>
	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Meeting Request/Proposal</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Allows <application>Evolution</application> users to
		  schedule meetings and view attendee availability for
		  other users (<application>Evolution</application> or
		  <application>Outlook</application> users) on
		  <application>Exchange</application>.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Adding iCalendar Meeting Requests to Calendar</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  If you receive an iCalendar meeting request and add it
		  to your calendar, it will be saved to your
		  <application>Exchange</application> calendar.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	  </variablelist>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Contacts
	  </para>
	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Address Completion</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Supported for your <application>Exchange</application>
		  Contacts folder.  Not yet supported for the Global
		  Address List.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Adding VCards to Address Book</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  If you receive a VCard attachment and click
		  <guibutton>Save in Address Book</guibutton>, it will
		  be saved to your <application>Exchange</application>address book.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>New Address Book entries can be created on
		<application>Exchange</application> from received email
		messages with a single click</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	  </variablelist>
	</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
There are, however, some features which are not available:
<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Work Offline (disconnected mode).
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
               "Recall Message" function.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="install">
    <title>Installing the Connector</title>
    <para>
       To install the Ximian Connector, run Ximian Red Carpet by
       selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guimenuitem>Get
       Software</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.  Subscribe to the Ximian
       Connector for Microsoft Exchange channel, select the Ximian
       Connector for Microsoft
       <application>Exchange</application>2000, and click the
       <guibutton>Install</guibutton> button.  You can also install
       the Connector by downloading the individual packages from
       ftp.ximian.com if you wish.
   </para>
   <para>
       Once you have installed the software, you will also need to
       install a license file.  The license file is the verification
       that you have paid for a license to use the Ximian
       Connector. You can get the license file from the the Ximian
       online store at <ulink
       url="http://store.ximian.com">store.ximian.com</ulink>.  You
       will need a browser with strong (128-bit or greater) encryption
       to access the store. When you purchase a Ximian Connector
       license, the store will mail you the license file with
       instructions for installation. Once installed, the license file
       unlocks the Ximian Connector functionality and you may connect
       to an <application>Exchange</application>server.
    </para>
 </sect1>

  <sect1 id="exchange-configure">
    <title>Adding your Exchange Account in Ximian Evolution</title>
    <para>
      Once you have installed the Connector, you need to set up access
      for your <application>Exchange</application>account on both the
      <application>Exchange</application>server and within Evolution.
    </para>

       <sect2 id="config-server">
       <title>Exchange Server Settings</title>
        <para>
	  Check with your system administrator to ensure that:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> 
	      You have a valid account on the <application>Exchange</application>server.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> You are permitted to access the account with
	      WebDAV. This is the default setting for the
	      <application>Exchange</application>server, so unless
	      your system administrator has specifically turned it
	      off, no changes should be necessary.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The Ximian website knowledge base, at <ulink type="http"
	url="http://support.ximian.com">support.ximian.com</ulink>,
	has additional information about checking to make sure that
	your <application>Exchange</application>server will accept
	connections from Ximian Evolution.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    

    <sect2 id="config-client">
      <title>Standard Configuration Tool for Ximian Connector</title>
      <para>
	Once you know that your server is ready for you to connect,
        you are ready to add your Exchange account to Ximian Connector.
     </para>


    <sect3 id="config-easy">
      <title>Simple Configuration Tool for Ximian Connector</title>
      <para>
        Ximian Connector 1.4 comes with a simple account creation tool
        for some installations. Other installations will require
        the standard account tool described in <xref
        linkend="config-client" /> below.
      </para>
      <para>
        The simple assistant works in the following cases:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If you receive your license key in Ximian Evolution, the
              simple assistant will start when you click the
              license file attachment and choose <guibutton>Open in
            Ximian Connector</guibutton>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you have no accounts configured, and your system
            administrator has preinstalled a license key file,            
            the simple assistant will start when you start <application>Ximian
            Evolution.</application> It asks only for the name of your Outlook
            Web Access server, and your username and password. Ximian
            Connector will determine the remaining information on its own.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
      <para>
        If the simple account tool does not run automatically, create
        an account as described below.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  

      <sect3 id="config-exchange-new-account">
	<title>Creating a New Exchange Account</title>

	
	<para>
	  If you would like to create a new account for your Exchange
          server, select <menuchoice>
	  <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
	  <guimenuitem>Mail Settings</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice>
          from any mail view. Then click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton>
          button in the accounts list. The account creation assistant
          will guide you through the process, which is also described in
          <xref linkend="usage-mainwindow-starting"/>. If you're not
          sure about any of the information you need, just ask your
          system administrator.
        </para>

     <note id="license-file-issues">
       <title>Installing the License File</title>
       <para>
         Your purchase email will contain instructions for installing
         the license file: it may be opened with Ximian Evolution and
         installed automatically that way, or placed in the
         <systemitem>evolution</systemitem> directory in your home
         directory.
       </para>
       <para>
         Be aware that the <systemitem>evolution</systemitem> directory in
         your home directory won't exist if you haven't already run 
         <application>Ximian Evolution</application>. If you have not
         done so already, start <application>Ximian
         Evolution</application> and configure an account as described
         below.  Then, quit the application and pllace the
         <systemitem>connector-key.data</systemitem> file in your
         <systemitem>evolution</systemitem> directory. When you start
         <application>Evolution</application> again, the license will
         be verified and Ximian Connector will work properly.
       </para>
     </note>


	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Identity</term>
	  <listitem>
	      <para>Enter your name and email address. If you wish,
	      you may add your organization and the location of your
	      signature file. Only your name and email address are
	      required.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Receiving Mail</term>
	  <listitem>
	      <para>
                In this step, you'll enter information about the way
                you check mail:
                 <orderedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
                      First, select <guilabel>Microsoft
                      Exchange</guilabel> as your server type.
                   </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
                     Enter the name of your Exchange email server, and
                     the user name you would use to log in to a
                     Windows workstation in your organization.
                   </para>
		  </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		    <para>
                      If you wish, select the box labeled
                      <guilabel>Use secure connection
                      (SSL)</guilabel>, to take advantage of a more
                      secure connection method. This may allow you to
                      connect to the server from outside your
                      firewall.
                   </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
                       If you would like
                       <application>Evolution</application> to
                       remember your password, check the box labeled
                       <guilabel>Remember this password</guilabel>.
                     </para>
		  </listitem>
		</orderedlist>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Receiving Mail, Step Two</term>
	  <listitem>
	      <para>There are a few additional options in this step:
               <orderedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
                       Checking for New Mail: If you would like to
                       check for new mail automatically, click the
                       checkbox and enter an interval in minutes.
                     </para>
		  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      Global Address List/Active Directory: Enter the
                      name of your global catalog server (directory
                      server). This will allow you to use the Global
                      Address List (GAL). Normally,
                      <application>Evolution</application> will fetch
                      a maximum of 500 responses to any query, but you
                      may increase or decrease this number if you
                      wish. A lower number decreases load on the
                      server, and many servers will refuse to return
                      more than 1000 results, no matter how many you
                      ask for.
                     </para>
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem>
		    <para>
                      Exchange Server: There are two options here:
                      <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>
                            Exchange mailbox name is different
                            from user name: If your exchange mailbox
                            name is different from your user name,
                            check this box and enter the mailbox name
                            here.
                          </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>
                            OWA path is not /exchange: In most cases,
                            the URL for Outlook Web Access is
                            "http://server.company.com/exchange." If your
                            system has a path that is not "/exchange," check
                            the box and enter the custom path here.
                          </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>
                            Public Folder Location: If your Exchange
                            system has a custom or nonstandard Public
                            Folder location, check this box and enter
                            the URL for public folders here.
                          </para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
	          <listitem>
		    <para>
                      Apply filters to new messages in Inbox on this
                      server: Check this box to filter messages in
                      this account.
                     </para>
		  </listitem>
		</orderedlist>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Sending Mail</term>
	  <listitem>
	      <para>Select <guilabel>Microsoft Exchange</guilabel> as
	      your email sending method. There is nothing else to do
	      in this step.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Account Management</term>
	  <listitem>
	      <para>Enter a name that you will use to remember this
	      account.  "Exchange Account" is a good suggestion. Note
	      that you cannot have two accounts with the same name.
	      If you'd like to make this your default account for
	      sending email, check the <guilabel>Make this my default
	      account</guilabel> box.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	<para>
          You're done.  Click <guibutton>Finish</guibutton> and
          <guibutton>OK</guibutton>, then quit
          <application>Evolution</application> and start it again. Now
          you're ready to get to work on the Exchange server.
        </para>

	<figure>
        <title>Creating an Exchange Account, Step One: Identity</title>
	<screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Creating an Exchange Account, Step One: Identity</screeninfo>
	  <mediaobject><imageobject>
	      <imagedata  format="PNG" fileref="figures/exchange-identity" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/>
	    </imageobject></mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>

	<figure>
        <title>Creating an Exchange Account, Step Two: Receiving Mail</title>
	<screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Creating an Exchange Account, Step Two: Receiving Mail</screeninfo>
	  <mediaobject><imageobject>
	      <imagedata  format="PNG" fileref="figures/exchange-receive" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/>
	    </imageobject></mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>

	<figure>
        <title>Creating an Exchange Account, Step Three: Mail Options</title>
	<screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Creating an Exchange Account, Step Three: Mail Options</screeninfo>
	  <mediaobject><imageobject>
	      <imagedata  format="PNG" fileref="figures/exchange-receive-options" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/>
	    </imageobject></mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>


      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="config-exchange-existing-account">
	<title>Changing an Existing Account to Work with Exchange</title>
	  <para>
	    If you have an existing email account, and want to convert it
	    to use for Exchange, select the account you want to convert
	    and click the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button. You'll want
	    to change settings in the following tabs of the account
	    dialog:
	  </para>
	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Identity</term>
	      <listitem>
	      <para>
		 If your email address will change because you are moving
		 to a new server, then change it in this tab. Otherwise,
		 move to the next tab.
	      </para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Receiving Mail</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Select <guilabel>Microsoft Exchange</guilabel> as your
		  server type. Enter your name of your server next to
		  <guilabel>Host</guilabel>, and the user name for your
		  account next to <guilabel>Username</guilabel>. If your
		  server supports SSL (Secure Socket Layer) encryption, it
		  you can check the <guilabel>Use SSL</guilabel> box to
		  take advantage of more secure data transfers.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Receiving Options</term>
	      <listitem>
		  <para>
		    Here, tab, you'll find some additional settings:
		    <variablelist>
		     <varlistentry>
		      <term>Checking for New Mail</term>
		       <listitem>
			 <para>
			    Select whether you would like to check for
			    mail automatically, and if so, how often.
			 </para>
		       </listitem>
		    </varlistentry>
		    <varlistentry>
		      <term>Mailbox Name and Web Access Path</term>
		       <listitem>
			 <para>
			   If your Exchange server requires you to use a
			   different mailbox name from the name you use to
			   log in, select the second check-box and enter
			   the mailbox name.  Check with your system
			   administrator to be sure.
			 </para>
	                 <para>
			   In most cases, the URL for web access is
			  "http://server.company.com/exchange." If your
			  system has a path that is not "exchange," check
			  the box and enter the custom path here.
			 </para>
		       </listitem>
		    </varlistentry>
		    <varlistentry>
		      <term>Active Directory</term>
		       <listitem>
			 <para>
			   If you would like to use the Global Address
			   List (GAL) maintained on your Exchange server,
			   click the tab labeled <guilabel>Receiving
			   Options</guilabel> and check the box labeled
			   <guilabel>Create a Global Address List
			   folder</guilabel>.  The GAL is maintained by
			   your system administrator and you cannot add,
			   change, or remove items from it using Ximian
			   Evolution. However, you can use it to invite
			   people to meetings and to look up addresses and
			   other information. In many organizations, the
			   GAL is stored on a different server from email.
			   If this is the case, you should also specify
			   the directory server name here.
			 </para>
		       </listitem>
		    </varlistentry>
		  </variablelist>
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Sending Mail</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  If you will use your Exchange server to send as well as
		  receive mail, select <guilabel>Microsoft
		  Exchange</guilabel> as your server type, and enter the
		  server name as the <guilabel>Host</guilabel>. 
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	  </variablelist>
	<para>

        Once you have made those changes, click the
        <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button.
      </para>
	<para>
          Then, quit <application>Evolution</application> and start it
          up again. Changes to the Ximian Connector accounts
          configuration are not active until you have restarted the
          application.
       </para>
      </sect3>      
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="access">
    <title>Accessing the <application>Exchange</application>Server</title>
    <para>
      Like IMAP and LDAP data, information for
      <application>Exchange</application>accounts is stored on the
      server, not on your desktop computer.  This means that you can
      access it from multiple locations. It also means that your
      Microsoft <application>Exchange</application>account information
      is in a separate folder tree from the <guilabel>Local</guilabel>
      tree in your folder bar. You'll see it below the local tree,
      with the name you gave the account. If you have multiple
      accounts, you will have multiple folder trees.
    </para>
    <para>
      Click on any of the folder tree items to visit them; you may
      have to enter your server password.  You can now create contact
      cards, send and receive email as you would normally. If there
      are items in your local calendar or addressbook that you'd like
      to add to your <application>Exchange</application>stores, you
      can copy and paste them over, or just drag items from one folder
      to another as you would with two local stores.
    </para>

      <note id="save-to-local-or-exchange">
	<title>Saving Attached Addresses and Appointments</title>
	<para>
          If you are using both an Exchange account and a local mail
          account, you should be aware that whenever you save an email
          address or appointment from an email message, it will be
          saved in your Exchange contacts list or calendar, rather
          than in your local account. The same is true of
          synchronization with Palm-OS devices: tasks, appointments,
          and addresses from your Palm-OS device will be synchronized
          with those in the Exchange folders rather than local
          folders.
       </para>
      </note>

   <tip id="gal-empty">
	<title>The Global Address List Appears Empty At First</title>
	<para>
          To avoid unnecessary strain on the server, the GAL will
          appear empty until you have searched for something in it.
          If you want to display all the cards in the list, click in
          the search box and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.  This
          enters a blank search: since every card contains a blank in
          it, every card will appear.
        </para>
      </tip>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="exchange-settings">
      <title>Special Connector Only Settings</title>
      <para>
        There are two items in the Evolution preferences window that
        are available only with Ximian Connector. The first is
        delegation and permissions handling, and the second is the
        creation of "Out of Office" messages.
      </para>

      <sect2 id="exchange-delegate">
        <title>Access Delegation</title>
        <para>
          You can allow other people in your organization's Global
          Address List  to access your calendar, address
          book, and messages, and they can let you manage theirs.
          Delegation allows people to do anything from check on each
          other's schedules to completely manage their personal
          information.
        </para>

        <sect3 id="exchange-delegate-to-others">
          <title>Delegating Access to Others</title>
        <para>
          To add someone to your list of delegates, click the
          <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button and select them from the
          Global Address List. When delegating you can grant different
          levels of access to different types of data. You may also
          decide whether the access you grant applies to items marked
          <guilabel>Private</guilabel>, or only to public items.
        </para>

        <para>
          For each of the four types of folder, you may select one of
          the following levels of access:
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>None</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Do not allow this person to access any folders of
                  this type.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Reviewer (read-only)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Allow the person to see items in this type of
                  folder, but not create new items or edit existing
                  items.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Author (read, create)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The delegate may view items in your folders, and may
                  create new items, but may not change any existing items.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Editor (read, create, edit)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The delegate may view, create, and change items in
                  your folders.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="exchange-delegated-to-you">
        <title>Acting as a Delegate for Others</title>
        <para>
          To see the list of people who have granted you access to
          their folders, click the <guilabel>Acting as a
          Delegate</guilabel> tab in the Exchange Delegation settings
          window. If you plan to send email on behalf of someone,
          click the checkbox next to their name, and an email identity
          will be created. You can then select that identity in the
          <guilabel>From</guilabel> list in your message composer.
        </para>

        <para>
          To access the folders delegated to you, do the following:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Select 
                <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>File</guimenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Open Other User's Folder</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Enter the email address of the user who
                has delegated to you or click the
                <guibutton>User</guibutton> button to select them from your
                addressbook. 
              </para>
            </listitem>
          
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Select the folder you wish to open.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>
                Click OK.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
          Folders delegated to you appear in your folder list inside a 
          folder labeled with the name of their owner. For example, if
          Martha Thompson delegates folders to you, you will see a
          folder called <guilabel>Martha Thompson's Folders</guilabel>
          in the folder tree at the same level as your <guilabel>Personal
          Folders</guilabel> and <guilabel>Public
          Folders</guilabel>. 
        </para>

        <note id="error">
          <title>Error Messages</title>
          <para>
            If the folder fails to open properly, check with the
            folder owner that you have been granted the correct access
            permissions.
          </para>
        </note>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

      
      <sect2 id="exchange-out-of-office">
        <title>Setting an Out of Office Message</title>
        <para>
          An <guilabel>Out of Office</guilabel> message is
          an automatic reply that you can send to emails, explaining why
          you aren't going to respond to their message. For example, if
          you go on vacation for a week and will be away from email, you
          can set an automatic reply so that people who write to you know
          that you aren't ignoring them.
        </para>
        <para>
          To create an <guilabel>Out of Office</guilabel> message,
        select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice> and then click the <guibutton>Out of
          Office</guibutton> button. 
        </para>

        <para>
          Then, click  <guilabel>I am currently
          out of the office.</guilabel>. Then, enter a short message in
          the text entry box. Click <guilabel>OK</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Your message will be sent automatically to
          anyone who sends you mail until you return and click
          <guilabel>I am currently in the office</guilabel>.
        </para>
      </sect2>


    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="full-advantage">
      <title>Scheduling Appointments with Free/Busy</title>
      <para>
        When you schedule a meeting with your calendar on the
        <application>Exchange</application>server, you can check when
        other local Exchange users are busy according to their
        <application>Exchange</application>calendars. To do so:
     </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Scheduling With Free/Busy Information</title>
	<screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Using the Free/Busy Feature</screeninfo>
	  <mediaobject><imageobject>
	      <imagedata  format="PNG" fileref="figures/schedule" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/>
	    </imageobject></mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>

       <note id="reminders-in-exchange">
         <title>Reminders In Exchange</title>
         <para>
          Reminders for appointments in your Exchange calendar will
          not work until you have run Evolution at least once after
          logging in. This is different from locally stored reminders,
          which will work from the moment you log in, regardless of
          whether you have run Evolution in the session.
         </para>
        </note>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
            Open a new appointment in the calendar.
          </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para> Choose <menuchoice> <guimenu>Actions</guimenu>
	      <guimenuitem>Schedule Meeting</guimenuitem>
	      </menuchoice> in the meeting editor window.
          </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para> Add attendees, either by entering their email
            addresses into the list, or by clicking the
            <guibutton>Invite Others</guibutton> button. If you choose
            to so, it's best to use the Global Address List (GAL).
            Choose the GAL from the drop-down list of address sources
            at the top of the dialog box.
         </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
          Choose <guilabel>Options</guilabel> and then
          <guilabel>Update Free/Busy</guilabel> to check participant
          schedules and, if possible, update the meeting in all
          participants' calendars.
         </para>
 	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <tip id="autopick">
	<title>Using Autopick to Adjust Meeting Times</title>
	<para>
         If meeting attendees are not available during the times you
         have scheduled a meeting, you can "nudge" the meeting forward
         or backward to the nearest available time.  To do so, just
         click the arrows to the left or right of the
         <guilabel>Autopick</guilabel> button. The autopick tool will
         move the meeting to the nearest time during which all
         attendees are available.  If you aren't satisfied with those
         results, you can drag the edges of the meeting time to the
         hours that you want to select.
      </para>
      </tip>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

