<chapter id="usage-mainwindow">

  <title>Getting Started with Ximian Evolution</title>

    <sect1 id="what"> 
      <title>What is Ximian Evolution, and What Can It Do for Me?</title>
      <para>
        Information is useless unless it's organized and accessible;
        it's hardly even worth the name if you can't look at it and be
        <emphasis>informed</emphasis>.  The goal of
        <application>Ximian Evolution</application> is to make the
        tasks of storing, organizing, and retrieving your personal
        information easier, so you can work and communicate with
        others.  That is, it's a highly evolved <glossterm
        linkend="groupware">groupware</glossterm> program, an integral
        part of the Internet-connected desktop.
      </para>
      <para>
        In other words, <application>Ximian Evolution</application> is
        a tool to help you get your work done. It can help you work in
        a group by handling email, address and other contact
        information, and one or more calendars.  It can do that on one
        or several computers, connected directly or over a network,
        for one person or for large groups.
      </para>

      <para>
        With <application>Ximian Evolution</application>, you can
        accomplish your most common daily tasks faster.  For example, it
        takes only one or two clicks to enter an appointment or an
        address card sent to you by email, or to send email to a contact
        or appointment.  <application>Ximian Evolution</application>
        makes displays faster and more efficient, so searches are faster
        and memory usage is lower.  People who get lots of mail will
        appreciate advanced features like <link
        linkend="usage-mail-organize-vfolders"><trademark>VFolders</trademark></link>,
        which let you save searches as though they were ordinary mail
        folders.
     </para>
   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="usage-mainwindow-starting">
     <title>The First Time you Start Ximian Evolution</title>
     <para>
       To start <application>Ximian Evolution</application>, do either
      of the following: 
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Programs</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Evolution</guimenuitem> </menuchoice> from your
      menu panel.
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
      <para>
      Type <command>evolution</command> at the command line.
      </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     </para>
 
     <para>
       <note>
         <title>Command Line Options</title>
         <para>
           Evolution has a number of command-line options that you may
           wish to make use of. You can find the full list by running
           the commands <userinput>man evolution</userinput> or
           <userinput>evolution --help</userinput>.  The most
           important ones are:
           <itemizedlist>
             <listitem>
               <para>
                 To start Evolution in offline mode: <userinput>evolution --offline</userinput> 
               </para>
             </listitem>

             <listitem>
               <para>
                 To start Evolution and begin composing a message to the email address you name: <userinput>evolution mailto:joe@somewhere.net</userinput>
             </para>
           </listitem>

           <listitem>
             <para>
               To make your web browser use Evolution as the default email client, enter <userinput>evolution "%s"</userinput> as the email handler in your web browser or in the GNOME Control Center.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </note>
  </para>
 <para>
     The first time you run the program, it will create a directory
      called <filename>evolution</filename> in your home directory,
      where it will store all of its local data.  Then, it will open a
      first-run assistant to help you set up mail accounts and import
      data from other applications.
    </para>
    <para>
      Using the first-run assistant will take approximately two to
      five minutes.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="first-step">
      <title>Defining Your Identity</title>
      <para>
	The Identity window is the first step in the assistant. Here,
	you will enter some basic personal information.  You can
	define multiple identities later on with the
	<menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Configure</guimenuitem></menuchoice> tool and
	clicking the <guibutton>Mail Accounts</guibutton> button.
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Full Name: Your full name (Example: John Doe).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Email Address: Your email address (Example: john@doe.com)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Reply-To: If you want to have replies sent to another
	      email address, enter it here (optional).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Organization: The company where you work, or the
	      organization you represent when you send email
	      (optional).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="second-step">
      <title>Receiving Email</title>
      <para>
        The <guilabel>Receiving Email</guilabel> lets you determine
	which you will get your email.
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Server Type: There are numerous types of servers
	      from which <application>Ximian Evolution</application>
	      can fetch your mail.  Ask your system administrator if
	      you're not sure which of the following are available to
	      you:
	      <itemizedlist>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    POP: Downloads your email to your hard disk for
		    permanent storage.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Microsoft Exchange: Available only if you have
		    purchased the Ximian Connector for Microsoft
		    Exchange, this will allow you to connect to a
		    Microsoft Exchange 2000 server, which stores
		    email, calendar, and contact information on the
		    server. 
		  </para>
		</listitem>


		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    IMAP: Keeps the email on your server so you can
		    access your email from multiple systems.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Standard Unix mbox spool or directory: If you want
		    to read and store mail in the mail spool on your
		    local system, choose this option. You'll need to
		    provide the path to the mail spool
		    you want to use.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Maildir format mail directories: If you download
		    your mail using qmail or another maildir-style
		    program, you'll want to use this option.  You'll need
		    to provide the path to the mail directory you want to
		    use.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    MH format mail directories: If you download your
		    mail using mh or another MH-style program, you'll
		    want to use this option.  You'll need to provide
		    the path to the mail directory you want to use.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Local Delivery: Choose this option if you want to
		    move mail from the spool and store it in your home
		    directory. If you would rather leave mail in your
		    system's spool files, choose the
		    <guimenuitem>Standard Unix mbox
		    spools</guimenuitem> option instead. You'll need
		    to provide the path to the mail spool you want to
		    use.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    None: Select this if you do not plan to
		    check mail with this account.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>

	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        If you selected POP, Microsoft Exchange, or IMAP as your mail
        server, you'll need to enter some more information:
      </para>
                     <itemizedlist>
		      <listitem>
			<para>The host name of your mail server. Ask
			your system administrator if you're not
			sure.</para>
		      </listitem>

		      <listitem>
			<para>The username for the account on that
			system. </para>
		      </listitem>

		      <listitem>
			<para>Whether you want to use a secure (SSL)
			connection. If your server supports it, it's
			best to enable this security option.
			</para>
		      </listitem>

		      <listitem>
			<para>The authentication options supported by
			your server. If you're not sure, click the
			<guilabel>Check for supported types</guilabel>
			button or ask your system administrator.
			</para>
		      </listitem>

		      <listitem>
			<para>Whether you'd like Evolution to remember
			your password.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
      <tip id="exchange-info">
	<title>Ximian Evolution Talk to Microsoft Exchange?</title>
         <para>
	   If you have purchased Ximian Connector for Microsoft
	   Exchange, you can access Microsoft Exchange 2000 servers
	   natively.  If you do not have the Connector, or if you use
	   an older version of Microsoft Exchange, talk to your system
	   administrator about access to standard protocol services
	   like POP and IMAP.
	</para>
      </tip> 

    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="more-mail-options">
      <title>More Mail Configuration Options</title>
      <para>
        There are more extensive options for mail preferences,
        especially if you've chosen POP, Microsoft Exchange, or IMAP
        as incoming mail server type.  If you want to set these
        options after you've created the account, you can select
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Configure
        </guimenuitem></menuchoice>, click the <guibutton>Mail
        Accounts</guibutton> button. Then, select the account you want
        to change and click <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>. See <xref
        linkend="config-prefs-mail"/> for details.
      </para>
        <variablelist>
	 <varlistentry>
	  <term>If you chose POP mail:</term>
	  <listitem><para>
         <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Checking for new mail: If you would like
	    <application>Evolution</application> to check for new mail
	    automatically, check the box and select a frequency in
	    minutes.
            </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              Message Storage: If you'd like to store copies of your
	    mail on the server, check this option.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
           </para>
 	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>If you chose Microsoft Exchange:</term>
	  <listitem><para>
        <itemizedlist> <listitem>
	    <para>Checking for new mail: If you would like
	    <application>Evolution</application> to check for new mail
	    automatically, check the box and select a frequency in
	    minutes.
            </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Mailbox Name is Different from Login Name: If your active directory user name
	    is different from your Exchange mailbox name, check this
	    box and enter your mailbox name here.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Override Outlook Web Access Path: In most cases,
	      the URL for web access is
	      "http://server.company.com/exchange." If your
	      system has a path that is not "exchange," check
	      the box and enter the custom path here.
	     </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Create a Global Address List folder: If you want to
	    use your organization's Active Directory or Global Address
	    List, leave this box checked. </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              Active Directory Server Name: Enter the Active Directory
	      server name here.
            </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Limit number of Responses: Select a maximum number
	    of results for an address search. A maximum number of
	    results limits the load on your system and on your network.
              </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>If you chose IMAP:</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
         <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Checking for new mail: If you would like
	    <application>Evolution</application> to check for new mail
	    automatically, check the box and select a frequency in
	    minutes.  
            </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>If you want <application>Evolution</application>
	    to check for new messages in <emphasis>all</emphasis> your
	    IMAP folders, make sure the <guilabel>Check for new
	    messages in all folders</guilabel> box is selected.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Show only subscribed folders: Check this box if you
	    have more folders in your IMAP view than you want to
	    read.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              Override server-supplied namespace: If you like, enter a
              specific directory where your server stores mail for
              you.  Typical values are "mail" and "Mail."  For more
              information about how to use IMAP mail, see <xref
              linkend="usage-mail-subscriptions"/>.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Apply filters to new messages in INBOX on this
	    server: If you'd like your filters to work on this account
	    as well as on locally downloaded mail, check this box.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
     </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>

         <note id="imap-namespace">
            <title>What's an IMAP Namespace?</title>
                <para>
                    For IMAP mail servers, your sysadmin may provide
		    you with a specific namespace, the directory on
		    where your server stores mail for you. If you
		    check your IMAP mail and your folder list includes
		    files that don't look like mail folders, you
		    probably need to change your mail
		    namespace. Typical values are "mail" and "Mail."
		    If you prefer, you can choose to subscribe to
		    individual mail folders one at a time. For more
		    information about how to use IMAP mail, see <xref
		    linkend="usage-mail-subscriptions"/>.
               </para>
             </note>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="third-step">
      <title>Sending Email</title>
      <para>
	The <guilabel>Sending Email</guilabel> step lets you configure sending 
	email.
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Server Type: There are numerous server types that
	      <application>Ximian Evolution</application> supports for sending your
	      mail.
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    SMTP: Sends mail directly from your system.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Microsoft Exchange: Sends mail through a Microsoft
		    Exchange server using the Microsoft Exchange 2000
		    protocol. Available only if you have are using the
		    Ximian Connector for Microsoft Exchange. You must
		    have a valid license key purchased from <ulink
		    url="http://store.ximian.com">store.ximian.com</ulink>.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Sendmail: Uses the Sendmail program to send mail
		    from your system. Sendmail is more flexible, but
		    is not as easy to configure, so you should only
		    select this option if you know how to set up a
		    Sendmail service.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Host: If you chose <guilabel>SMTP</guilabel> or
	      <guilabel>Microsoft Exchange</guilabel>, enter the
	      server's name or IP address here.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Server requires authentication: If your server
	      requires you to enter a password to send mail, check
	      this box.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Authentication Type: Unless you've been told otherwise,
	      your best bet is to leave this set at
	      <guilabel>Password</guilabel>.  If you're not sure, ask
	      your system administrator or ISP, or have
	      <application>Ximian Evolution</application> check for
	      you by clicking <guibutton>Check for supported
	      types</guibutton>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Username: The account name you use when you login to
	      check your email.  Normally, this is the part of your
	      email address before the '@' character. For Exchange
	      servers, it is the username you would use to log in to a
	      Windows workstation at your company.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Remember Password: If you prefer to not enter
	      your password every time you check email, press this
	      button.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="step-three-b">
      <title>Account Management</title>
      <para>
        This is a very short section. You can pick two things: the
        name for the account, and whether it is the default account.
      </para>
      <para>
        The name you choose for the account is used for display within
        Evolution, and is not sent with any emails.  The suggested
        name is your email address, but you can use other words or
        phrases, like "Work," "Personal" or "First Account" if you
        like.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you check the box next to the label <guilabel>Make this my
      default account</guilabel>, Evolution will assume that you will
      send messages from this most often, and will set the
      "From" selector to this account whenever you open a new message. Only one account can be the default.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you have not done so already, you may also be asked to choose
      a time zone.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="fourth-step">
      <title>Importing Mail (Optional)</title>
      <para>
	If <application>Ximian Evolution</application> finds mail or
	address files from another application, it will offer to
	import them.  If you're not sure which file format your mail
	program uses, ask your system administrator.  If you want, you
	can skip this step and return to it at a later time by
	selecting
	<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Import</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para>
	<application>Ximian Evolution</application> can import the following types of
	files:
          <variablelist>
           <varlistentry>
	    <term>VCard (.vcf, gcrd):</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	         The addressbook format used by the GNOME, KDE, and
	         many other contact management applications. You
	         should be able to export to VCard format from any
	         address book application.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Microsoft Outlook Express 4 (.mbx):</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
                 Email file format used by Microsoft Outlook Express
4. For other versions of Microsoft Outlook and Outlook Express, see
the workaround described in the note below.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>MBox (mbox):</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	       The email box format used by Mozilla, Netscape,
	       Ximian Evolution, Eudora, and many other email clients.
  	     </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
       </variablelist>
</para>
<para>
    <note>
      <title>Microsoft Outlook and Outlook Express Users</title>
      <para>
	Microsoft Outlook, and versions of Outlook Express after
	version 4, use proprietary formats that <application>Ximian
	Evolution</application> cannot read or import.  For contacts,
	you may have to email them to yourself and import them that
	way.  For email, there is a simpler workaround:
	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">

	<listitem>
	<para>
	  While using Windows, import the files into Mozilla Mail (or
	  another mailer, such as Netscape or Eudora, that uses the
	  standard mbox format).
        </para>
        </listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
          Copy the files to the system or partition you use for
          <application>Ximian Evolution</application>.  
         </para>
        </listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	  Use the <application>Ximian Evolution</application> import
          tool to import the files.  There's more information about
          why this works, and how, at the Ximian <ulink
          url="http://support.ximian.com">support website.</ulink>
      </para>
        </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
    </para>
    </note>     

    <note>
      <title>Netscape Users</title>
      <para>
	Before importing mail from Netscape, make sure you select
	<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Compact All
	Folders</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. If you don't,
	<application>Ximian Evolution</application> will import and undelete
	the messages in your Trash folders.
      </para>
    </note>     

    </para>

      <tip>
	<title>Exporting Files From Ximian Evolution</title>
	<para>
          Ximian Evolution uses standard file types for all its information,
          so you should have no trouble taking your information
          elsewhere if you want.
        </para>
	<para>
          For mail, that's <filename>mbox</filename>, for calendar,
          <filename>iCal</filename>, and for the address book, vCards
          in a <filename>.db3</filename> database.
        </para>
      </tip>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="importing-mail-from-clients">
    <title>Importing Mail from Other Mail Clients</title>
    <para>
      Chances are, you already have your email in another mail program
      and don't want to lose the information.  The following section
      describes how to import mail from specific mail clients.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="mutt">
      <title>Importing Mail from mutt</title>
      <para>
	<application>mutt</application> is a text-based mail client
	which is shipped with many Linux and Unix distributions.
	<application>mutt</application> uses the standard mbox,
	maildir, and MH file formats, which makes importing your mail
	into <application>Evolution</application> easy.  By default,
	<application>mutt</application> uses the mbox file format.
	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Open <application>Ximian Evolution</application>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click
	      <menuchoice>
		<guimenu>File</guimenu>
		<guimenuitem>Import</guimenuitem>
	      </menuchoice>
	      or press
	      <keycombo action="simul">
		<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
		<keycap>I</keycap>
	      </keycombo>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Select <guibutton>Import a Single File</guibutton>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> and select the file
	      you would like to import from.  By default, your email
	      is stored in <filename>~/mbox</filename> for the mbox
	      format and <filename
	      class="directory">~/Maildir</filename> for the Maildir format.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      When prompted for what folder in
	      <application>Evolution</application> to import to,
	      select a folder.  You can also create a new folder and
	      drop it in there.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="kmail">
      <title>Importing Mail from KMail</title>
      <para>
	KMail is the mail client which is shipped with the KDE desktop
	environment.  KMail uses the standard mbox file format, which
	means that importing your mail into
	<application>Evolution</application> is easy.
	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Open <application>Ximian Evolution</application>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click
	      <menuchoice>
		<guimenu>File</guimenu>
		<guimenuitem>Import</guimenuitem>
	      </menuchoice>
	      or press
	      <keycombo action="simul">
		<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
		<keycap>I</keycap>
	      </keycombo>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Select <guibutton>Import a Single File</guibutton>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> and select the file
	      you would like to import from.  By default, KMail stores
	      its information in the Mail directory of your home
	      directory.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      When prompted for what folder in
	      <application>Evolution</application> to import to,
	      select a folder.  You can also create a new folder and
	      drop it in there.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="ui-intro">
    <title>What's What in Ximian Evolution</title>
    <para>
        Now that you've gotten the first-run configuration out of the
        way, you're ready to get down to work.  Here's a quick
        explanation of what's going on in your main
        <application>Ximian Evolution</application> window.
    </para>

    <figure id="preface-basic-interface">
      <title>The Ximian Evolution Main Window</title>
      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Inbox</screeninfo>
	  <mediaobject>
             <imageobject>
                 <imagedata fileref="figures/mainwindow-pic" format="PNG" srccredit="Kevin Breit"/> 
             </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata  fileref="figures/full-1" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
      <guilabel>Menu Bar</guilabel>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <guilabel>menu bar</guilabel> gives you access to nearly all
      the features that can be found in <application>Ximian
      Evolution</application>.
    </para>

    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-2" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
      <guilabel>Toolbar</guilabel>
    </para>

    <para>
      The <guilabel>Toolbar</guilabel> gives you fast and easy access to the
      most used features in each component.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-3" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
      <guilabel>Shortcut Bar</guilabel>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <guilabel>Shortcut Bar</guilabel> lets you go to your favorite
      components with the click of a click of a button.  
    </para>
    
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-4" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
      <guilabel>Status Bar</guilabel>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Periodically, <application>Ximian Evolution</application> will need to quietly
      display a message, or tell you the progress of a task.  This most
      often happens when you're checking or sending email.  These progress
      queues are shown here, in the <guilabel>Status Bar</guilabel>.  
    </para>
    
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-5" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
      <guilabel>Search Tool</guilabel>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <guilabel>Search Tool</guilabel> lets you search through your email
      with precision so you can easily find what you're looking for.
    </para>


  <sect2 id="usage-mainwindow-shortcutbar">
    <title>The Shortcut Bar</title>
    <para>
        <application>Ximian Evolution</application>'s most important job is
        to give you access to your information and help you use it
        quickly.  One way it does that is through the
        <interface>shortcut bar</interface>, the column on the left
        hand side of the main window.  The large buttons with names
        like <guilabel>Inbox</guilabel> and
        <guilabel>Contacts</guilabel> are the shortcuts, and you can
        select different groups of shortcuts by clicking the
        rectangular group buttons.
    </para>
    <para>
       Take a look at the <guilabel>Shortcut Bar</guilabel>
       The shortcut buttons in that category are:

	    <variablelist>
	      <varlistentry>
		<term> <guibutton>Summary</guibutton>:</term>
		<listitem>
	    <para>
		    Start your day here.  The Ximian Evolution
		    <guilabel>Summary</guilabel> gives you a quick
		    summary of new or important messages, daily
		    appointments and urgent tasks.  You can customize
		    its appearance and content, and use it to access
		    Ximian Evolution services.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term> <guibutton>Inbox</guibutton>:</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click the <guibutton>Inbox</guibutton> button to start
	      reading your mail.  Your Inbox is also where you can
	      access Ximian Evolution's tools to filter, sort, organize, and
	      search your mail.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guibutton>Calendar</guibutton>:</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The Calendar can store your appointments and task lists
	      for you.  Connected to a network, you can use it to keep
	      a group of people on schedule and up to date.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
         <term><guibutton>Tasks</guibutton>:</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	     A full-size view of your calendar's task pad.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term><guibutton>Contacts</guibutton>:</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The Addressbook holds contacts, with address, phone, and
	      other personal information. Like calendar information,
	      contact data can be synchronized with hand-held devices
	      and shared over a network.
	   </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>	  
	</variablelist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="usage-mainwindow-folderbar">
    <title>Folders and The Folder Bar</title>
    <para>
      The <interface>folder bar</interface> is a more comprehensive
      way to view the information you've stored with
      <application>Ximian Evolution</application>. It displays all your
      appointments, address cards, and email in a tree that's a lot
      like a <glossterm linkend="filetree">file
      tree</glossterm>-- it starts small at the top, and branches
      downward. On most computers, there will be three or four
      folders at the base.  First, of course, is the
      <guilabel>Summary</guilabel>, a customizable summary of your
      information. Below that are your <guilabel>Local
      Folders</guilabel>, which hold all the
      <application>Ximian Evolution</application> data that's stored on your
      computer.  After that are your network servers: <glossterm
      linkend="ldap">LDAP</glossterm> servers that host shared contact
      directories, and <glossterm linkend="imap">IMAP</glossterm> mail
      folders to which you subscribe.  Lastly, there are
      <guilabel>vFolders</guilabel>, or virtual folders, discussed in
      <xref linkend="usage-mail-organize-vfolders"/>,
    </para>
    <para>
       
      A typical <guilabel>Local</guilabel> folder contains the following folders:
      <itemizedlist>
	 <listitem>
	    <para>
	     <guilabel>Calendar</guilabel>, for appointments and
	     event listings.
	   </para>
	 </listitem> 
	 <listitem>
	    <para>
	    <guilabel>Contacts</guilabel>, for address cards.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
         <listitem>
	    <para>
	    <guilabel>Drafts</guilabel>, for messages you started and didn't finish.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>
	    <para>
	     <guilabel>Inbox</guilabel>, for incoming mail. 
	   </para>
	 </listitem>

	<listitem>
	   <para>
	    <guilabel>Outbox</guilabel>, for messages you have written
	    but not yet sent.  This will be empty unless you use
	    <application>Ximian Evolution</application> while offline.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>

	<listitem>
	   <para>
	    <guilabel>Sent</guilabel>, for sent mail.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>

	<listitem>
	   <para>
	    <guilabel>Tasks</guilabel>, for your task list. Portions
            of your task list are reflected in the calendar, as well
            as in the summary folder.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>

	<listitem>
	    <para>
	    <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>, a vFolder view of all the
	    messages you have marked for deletion but not yet
	    <glossterm linkend="expunge">expunged</glossterm>.
	   </para>
	 </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </para>
    <tip id="foldertips">
    <title>Navigating without the Folder Bar or the Shortcut Bar</title>
       <para>
         You don't need the folder bar or the shortcut bar to move
         around the main window. You can use the <keycap>Tab</keycap>
         key to switch from one part of the window to another. When
         you hide the folder bar, there is a menu on the left side of
         the window just below the toolbar to move about the folder
         tree, even with the folder and shortcut bars hidden.
       </para>
     </tip>

    <para>
       If you get large volumes of mail, you'll want more folders than
       just your Inbox.  To create a new folder:
	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Select
	      <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
		<guisubmenu>New</guisubmenu>
		<guimenuitem>Folder</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
	or press the keyboard shortcut 
                <keycombo action="simul">
		<keycap>Shift</keycap>
		<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
		<keycap>E</keycap>
	      </keycombo>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Select the name of the folder in the <guilabel>Folder
		Name</guilabel> field.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Select the folder type.  The available options are.
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Calendar
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Contacts
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Mail
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Tasks
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>

	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Choose the location of the new folder.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    
    <sect3 id="subfolders">
    <title>Subfolders</title>
      <para>
        <application>Ximian Evolution</application> lets you nest folders
	inside of each other, so that you can have a detailed
	organizational system.
      </para>

       <note>
	  <title>Folders Have Limits</title>
	  <para>
              Calendars must go in calendar folders, mail in mail
	      folders, and contacts in contact folders.
           </para>
	</note>

    <para>
      Right-clicking will bring up a menu for just about anything in
      <application>Ximian Evolution</application>.  If you right-click on a
      folder, you'll have a menu with the following options:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>View</guimenuitem>, to view the folder. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Open in New Window</guimenuitem> to view the folder in another window. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Move</guimenuitem>, to move the folder to another location. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem>, to duplicate the folder. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>, to delete the folder and all its contents. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Rename</guimenuitem>, to change its name. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Create New Folder</guimenuitem>, to create another folder in the same location. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Add to Shortcut Bar</guimenuitem>, to add the folder to your shortcut bar. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>, to view or change the folder properties. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      You can also rearrange folders and messages by dragging and
      dropping them.
    </para>

	<para>
	  Any time new mail arrives in a mail folder, that folder
	  label is displayed in bold text, along with the number of
	  new messages in that folder.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="usage-mainwindow-menubar">
    <title>The Menu Bar</title>
    <para>
      The <interface>menu bar</interface>'s contents will always
      provide all the possible actions for any given view of your
      data.  If you're looking at your Inbox, most of the menu items
      will relate to mail; some will relate to other components of
      <application>Ximian Evolution</application> and some, especially those
      in the <guimenu>File Menu</guimenu> will relate to the
      application as a whole. 
   </para> 
   <para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>File</guimenu>:</term>

          <listitem><para> Anything related to a file or to the
            operations of the application generally falls under this
            menu: creating things, saving them to disk, printing them,
            and quitting the program itself.  </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
              The <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu holds
              useful tools that help you edit text and move it around.
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>View</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
            This menu lets you decide how <application>Ximian Evolution</application> 
            should look. Some of the features control the appearance of 
            <application>Ximian Evolution</application> as a whole, and others 
            the way a particular kind of information appears.
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>Actions</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
	    Holds actions which maybe applied to a message.  Normally,
	    if there is only one target for the action -- for
	    example, replying to a message -- you can find it in
	    the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu.
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
             Tools for configuring, changing, and
          setting up  go here.  For mail, that means things like
           and the
          <guimenuitem>Virtual Folder Editor</guimenuitem>.  For the
          <interface>Calendar</interface> and the <interface>Contact
          Manager</interface>, it's color, network, and layout
          configuration.
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>



       <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>Search</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
             Select menu items here to search for messages, or for
          phrases within a message. You can also see previous searches
          you have made.  In addition to the <guimenu>Search</guimenu>
          menu, there is a text entry box in the toolbar that you can
          use to search for messages.
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>Help</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
             Select among these items to open the 
             <application>Help Browser</application> 
             and read the <application>Ximian Evolution</application> manual.
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
   </para>

   <para>
      Once you've familiarized yourself with the <interface>main
      window</interface> you can start doing things with it.  We'll
      start with the <guilabel>Summary</guilabel>, which provides a
      quick overview of your <application>Ximian
      Evolution</application> information.
    </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="basics-summary">
      <title>Introducing the Summary</title>
      <para>
         The Ximian Evolution Summary provides you with a quick
         run-down of important information: your appointments for a
         given day, how much new mail you have, headlines from
         selected news services, and so forth. To see the Summary,
         click on the <guibutton>Summary</guibutton> button in the
         shortcut bar, or select the <guilabel>Summary</guilabel>
         folder in the folder bar.
      </para>

      <para>
<figure>
	<title>The Evolution Summary</title>

<screenshot>
<graphic  format="PNG" fileref="figures/summary" srccredit="Kevin Breit"/>
</screenshot>
</figure>
      </para>

<para>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/full-1" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Weather Summary</guilabel>
</para>
<para>
Shows you the latest weather updates from hundreds of cities around the world.
</para>
<para>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/full-2" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>News Feeds</guilabel>
</para>
<para>
Displays up to the minute news from your favorite websites.
</para>
<para>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/full-3" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Mail Summary</guilabel>
</para>
<para>
Shows you how many email messages you have in your selected folders, waiting to be read.
</para>
<para>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/full-4" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Calendar Summary</guilabel>
</para>
<para>
Shows you your calendar.
</para>
<para>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/full-5" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Tasks</guilabel>
</para>
<para>
Shows your pending tasks
</para>


      <para>
        To add additional services to your Summary, or to edit the
        existing services, select
        <menuchoice>
	  <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
	  <guimenuitem>Configure</guimenuitem> </menuchoice> and click
	  the <guibutton>Summary Settings</guibutton> button.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-mail">
      <title>Introducing Email</title>
      <para>
         <application>Ximian Evolution</application> email is like other
         email programs in several ways:
     <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              It can sort and organize your mail in a wide variety of
              ways with folders, searches, and filters.
           </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              It can send and receive mail in HTML or as plain text,
              and makes it easy to send and receive multiple file
              attachments.
           </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              It supports multiple mail sources, including <glossterm
              linkend="imap">IMAP</glossterm>, <glossterm
              linkend="pop">POP3</glossterm>, and local
              <filename>mbox</filename> or <filename>mh</filename>
              spools and files created by other mail programs.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      It lets you guard your privacy with encryption.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        However, <application>Ximian Evolution</application> has some
        important differences.  First, it's built to handle very large
        amounts of mail.  Both the <link
        linkend="usage-mail-organize-filters">filtering</link> and
        <link linkend="usage-mail-organize-search">searching</link>
        functions were built for speed and efficiency on large volumes
        of mail. There's also the <application>Ximian Evolution</application>
        <link linkend="usage-mail-organize-vfolders">vFolder</link>,
        an advanced organizational feature not found in mainstream
        mail clients.  If you get a lot of mail, or if you keep every
        message you get in case you need to refer to it later, you'll
        find this feature especially useful.
     </para>
     <para>
        Here's what the mailer looks like:

 <!-- ==============Figure=================================== -->

      <figure id="usage-mail-intro-fig">
          <title>Ximian Evolution Mail</title>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Inbox</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/mail-inbox" format="PNG" srccredit="Kevin Breit"/>
        </imageobject></mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
<!-- ==============End of Figure============================== -->
</para>
      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-1"
        format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Email
        Viewer</guilabel>
      </para>
    
      <para>
        This is where your email is displayed.
      </para>

      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-2"
        format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Message List</guilabel>
      </para>
    
      <para>
        The <guilabel>Message List</guilabel> displays all the emails
        that you have.  This includes all your read, unread, and email
        that is flagged to be deleted.
      </para>

      <para>
     If you find the <interface>view pane</interface> too small, you can resize
        the pane, enlarge the whole window, or double-click on the
        message in the <interface>message list</interface> to have it
        open in a new window.  To change the sizes of a pane, just click
        and hold on the divider between the two panes.  Then you can drag
        up and down to select the size of the panes.

</para>
<para> Just like with folders, you can right-click on messages in the
        message list and get a menu of possible actions: you can move,
        delete, or undelete them, and create filters or vFolders based
        on them.
      </para>
      <para>
        Most of the mail-related actions you'll want to perform are
        listed in the <guimenu>Message</guimenu> menu in the menu bar.
        The most frequently used ones, like
        <guimenuitem>Reply</guimenuitem> and
        <guimenuitem>Forward</guimenuitem>, also appear as buttons in
        the toolbar. Almost all of them are also located in the
        right-click menu and as keyboard shortcuts, which tend to be
        faster once you get the hang of them.  You can choose
        whichever way you like best; the idea is that the software
        should work the way you want, rather than making you work the
        way the it does.
      </para>

       <para>
         For an in-depth guide to the email capabilities of Ximian
         Evolution, read <xref linkend="usage-mail"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="basics-calendar">
      <title>Introducing the Calendar</title>
      <para>
       To begin using the calendar, select
       <guibutton>Calendar</guibutton> from the <interface>shortcut
       bar</interface>.  By default, the calendar starts showing
       today's schedule on a ruled background.  At the upper right,
       there's a monthly calendar you can use to switch days.  Below
       that, there's a <guilabel>Task</guilabel> pad, where you can
       keep a list of tasks separate from your calendar appointments.
       The day view in the calendar looks like this:

   <!-- ============== Figure ============================= -->
    <figure id="usage-calendar-fig">
      <title>Ximian Evolution Calendar View</title>
      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Ximian Evolution Contact Manager Window</screeninfo>
	<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/calendar" format="PNG" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/>
	</imageobject></mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  <!-- ============== End of Figure ============================= --> 

    </para>

      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-1"
        format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Appointment
        List</guilabel>
      </para>
  
      <para>
	The <guilabel>Appointment List</guilabel> is responsible for showing you all of
	your scheduled appointments, whether they are all day appointments or simply one time
	appointments that last a half an hour.
      </para>

      <para>
	<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-2" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
	<guilabel>Task List</guilabel>
      </para>

      <para>
        The <guilabel>Task List</guilabel> compliments the
        <guilabel>Appointment List </guilabel> as it keeps track of
        tasks which don't have a time associated with them. Tasks can
        have complex notes associated with them, and you can also note
        their completeness on a percentage scale.
      </para>

      <para>
	<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-3" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
	<guilabel>Calendar Window</guilabel>
      </para>

      <para>
	The <guilabel>Calendar Window</guilabel> has a graphical representation of
	the calendar, so you can select what days to view in the <guilabel>Appointment
	List</guilabel>.
      </para>

      <para>
          For more information about the calendar
          read <xref linkend="usage-calendar"/>.
      </para>

    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="basics-contacts">
      <title>Introducing the Address Book</title>
      <para>
        The <application>Ximian Evolution</application> address book
        can handle all of the functions of an address book, phone
        book, or Rolodex.  Of course, it's a lot easier to update
        <application>Ximian Evolution</application> than it is to
        change an actual paper book. <application>Ximian
        Evolution</application> also allows easy synchronization with
        hand-held devices and functions with <glossterm
        linkend="ldap">LDAP</glossterm> directories on a network.
      </para>
      <para>
        Another advantage of the <application>Ximian Evolution</application>
        address book is its integration with the rest of the
        application.  For example, you can create an address card from
        an email just by right-clicking on the sender's email address.
      </para>
      <para>
        To open your address book, click on
        <guibutton>Contacts</guibutton> in the shortcut bar, or select
        one of your contacts folders from the folder bar.  <xref
        linkend="usage-contact-fig"/> shows the address book in all its
        organizational glory.  By default, the address book shows all
        your cards in alphabetical order, in a <glossterm
        linkend="minicard">minicard</glossterm> view.  You can select
        other views from the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu, and adjust
        the width of the columns by clicking and dragging the gray
        column dividers.
      </para>
      <para>
        The address book looks like this:

      <figure id="usage-contact-fig">
	<title>Ximian Evolution Contact Interface</title>
	<screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Ximian Evolution Contact List Window</screeninfo>
	  <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/contact" format="PNG" srccredit="Kevin Breit"/>
  	  </imageobject></mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>
     </para>
      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-1"
        format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Contact
        List</guilabel>
      </para>
      <para>
        The <guilabel>Contact List</guilabel> lists your contacts.
      </para>
      <para>
          For detailed instructions on how to use the address book,
          read <xref linkend="usage-contact"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>