<chapter id="usage-mainwindow">

  <title>Getting Started with Novell Evolution</title>

    <sect1 id="what"> 
      <title>What is Novell Evolution, and What Can It Do for Me?</title>
      <para>
        Information is useless unless it's organized and accessible;
        it's hardly even worth the name if you can't look at it and be
        <emphasis>informed</emphasis>.  The goal of
        Novell Evolution is to make the
        tasks of storing, organizing, and retrieving your personal
        information easier, so you can work and communicate with
        others.  That is, it's a highly evolved <glossterm
        linkend="groupware">groupware</glossterm> program, an integral
        part of the Internet-connected desktop.
      </para>
      <para>
        In other words, Novell Evolution is
        a tool to help you get your work done. It can help you work in
        a group by handling email, address and other contact
        information, and one or more calendars.  It can do that on one
        or several computers, connected directly or over a network,
        for one person or for large groups.
      </para>

      <para>
        With Novell Evolution, you can
        accomplish your most common daily tasks faster.  For example, it
        takes only one or two clicks to enter appointment or
        contact information sent to you by email, or to send email to a contact
        or appointment.  Novell Evolution
        makes displays faster and more efficient, so searches are faster
        and memory usage is lower.  People who get lots of mail will
        appreciate advanced features like <link
        linkend="usage-mail-organize-vfolders"><trademark>VFolders</trademark></link>,
        which let you save searches as though they were ordinary mail
        folders.
     </para>
   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="usage-mainwindow-starting">
     <title>The First Time you Start Novell Evolution</title>
     <para>
       To start Novell Evolution, do either
      of the following: 
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Programs</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Evolution</guimenuitem> </menuchoice> from your
      menu panel.
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
      <para>
      Type <command>evolution</command> at the command line.
      </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     </para>
 
     <para>
       <note>
         <title>Command Line Options</title>
         <para>
           Evolution has a number of command-line options that you may
           wish to make use of. You can find the full list by running
           the commands <userinput>man evolution</userinput> or
           <userinput>evolution --help</userinput>.  The most
           important ones are:
           <itemizedlist>
             <listitem>
               <para>
                 To start Evolution in offline mode: <userinput>evolution --offline</userinput> 
               </para>
             </listitem>

             <listitem>
               <para>
                 To start Evolution and begin composing a message to the email address you name: <userinput>evolution mailto:joe@somewhere.net</userinput>
             </para>
           </listitem>

           <listitem>
             <para>
               To make your web browser use Evolution as the default
               email client, enter <userinput>evolution "%s"</userinput> as the email
               handler in your web browser or in the GNOME Control Center.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </note>
  </para>
 <para>
     The first time you run the program, it will create a directory
      called <filename>.evolution</filename> in your home directory,
      where it will store all of its local data.  Then, it will open a
      first-run assistant to help you set up mail accounts and import
      data from other applications.
    </para>
    <para>
      Using the first-run assistant will take approximately two to
      five minutes.
    </para> 
    <para>
      Later on, if you want to change the account you are creating, or
      if you want to create a new one,select
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Configure
        </guimenuitem></menuchoice>, and click the <guilabel>Mail
        Accounts</guilabel> button. Then, select the account you want
        to change and click <guilabel>Edit</guilabel>, or click
        <guilabel>Add</guilabel> to add a new account. See <xref
        linkend="config-prefs-mail"/> for details.
      </para>

    <sect2 id="first-step">
      <title>Defining Your Identity</title>
      <para>
	The Identity window is the first step in the assistant. Here,
	you will enter some basic personal information.  You can
	define multiple identities later on with the
	<menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice> tool and
	clicking the <guilabel>Mail Accounts</guilabel> button.
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Full Name: Your full name (Example: John Doe).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Email Address: Your email address (Example: john@doe.com)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Reply-To: If you want to have replies sent to another
	      email address, enter it here (optional).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Organization: The company where you work, or the
	      organization you represent when you send email
	      (optional).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="second-step">
      <title>Receiving Email</title>
      <para>
        The <guilabel>Receiving Email</guilabel> lets you determine
	which you will get your email.
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Server Type: There are numerous types of servers
	      from which Novell Evolution
	      can fetch your mail.  Ask your system administrator if
	      you're not sure which of the following are available to
	      you:
	      <itemizedlist>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    GroupWise: Select this option if you use a
                    GroupWise server. GroupWise keeps mail, calendar,
                    and contact information on the server.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Microsoft Exchange: Available only if you have
		    installed the Novell Connector for Microsoft
		    Exchange, this will allow you to connect to a
		    Microsoft Exchange 2000 or 2003 server, which
                    stores email, calendar, and contact information on
                    the server.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    IMAP: Keeps the email on your server so you can
		    access your email from multiple systems.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    POP: Downloads your email to your hard disk for
		    permanent storage.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Local Delivery: Choose this option if you want to
		    move mail from the spool and store it in your home
		    directory. If you would rather leave mail in your
		    system's spool files, choose the
		    <guimenuitem>Standard Unix mbox
		    spools</guimenuitem> option instead. You'll need
		    to provide the path to the mail spool you want to
		    use.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    MH format mail directories: If you download your
		    mail using mh or another MH-style program, you'll
		    want to use this option.  You'll need to provide
		    the path to the mail directory you want to use.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Maildir format mail directories: If you download
		    your mail using qmail or another maildir-style
		    program, you'll want to use this option.  You'll need
		    to provide the path to the mail directory you want to
		    use.
		  </para>
		</listitem>


		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Standard Unix mbox spool or directory: If you want
		    to read and store mail in the mail spool on your
		    local system, choose this option. You'll need to
		    provide the path to the mail spool
		    you want to use.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    None: Select this if you do not plan to
		    check mail with this account.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>

	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        If you selected POP, Microsoft Exchange, or IMAP as your mail
        server, you'll need to enter some more information:
      </para>
                     <itemizedlist>
		      <listitem>
			<para>The host name of your mail server. Ask
			your system administrator if you're not
			sure.</para>
		      </listitem>

		      <listitem>
			<para>The username for the account on that
			system. </para>
		      </listitem>

		      <listitem>
			<para>Whether you want to use a secure (SSL)
			connection. If your server supports it, it's
			best to enable this security option.
			</para>
		      </listitem>

		      <listitem>
			<para>The authentication options supported by
			your server. If you're not sure, click the
			<guilabel>Check for supported types</guilabel>
			button or ask your system administrator.
			</para>
		      </listitem>

		      <listitem>
			<para>Whether you'd like Evolution to remember
			your password.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>

      <tip id="exchange-info">
	<title>Use Novell Evolution with Microsoft Exchange</title>
         <para>
	   If you have installed Novell Connector for Microsoft
	   Exchange, you can access Microsoft Exchange 2000 servers
	   natively.  If you do not have the Connector, or if you use
	   an older version of Microsoft Exchange, talk to your system
	   administrator about access to standard protocol services
	   like POP and IMAP.
	</para>
      </tip> 

    </sect2>


    <sect2 id="more-mail-options">
      <title>More Mail Configuration Options</title>
      <para>
        Once you have selected a mail delivery mechanism, you may
        set some preferences for its behavior:
      </para>
        <variablelist>
	 <varlistentry>
	  <term>If you chose POP mail:</term>
	  <listitem><para>
         <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Checking for new mail: If you would like
	    Evolution to check for new mail
	    automatically, check the box and select a frequency in
	    minutes.
            </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              Message Storage: If you'd like to store copies of your
	    mail on the server, check this option.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
           </para>
 	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>If you chose Microsoft Exchange:</term>
	  <listitem><para>
        <itemizedlist> <listitem>
	    <para>Checking for new mail: If you would like
	    Evolution to check for new mail
	    automatically, check the box and select a frequency in
	    minutes.
            </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              Global Address List/Active Directory: Enter the name of
              your global catalog server here. You may also choose to
              limit the server's responses and select a maximum number
              of results for an address search. A maximum number of
              results limits the load on your system and on your
              network.
            </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Mailbox Name: If your active directory user name is
	    different from your Exchange mailbox name, enter the
	    mailbox name here.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Outlook Web Access (OWA) Path: In most cases, the URL
	      for web access is "http://server.company.com/exchange."
	      If your system has a path that is not "exchange," enter
	      the appropriate value here.
	     </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Public Folder Server: Enter the name of your organization's public folder server, if any, here.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Apply filters to new messages in Inbox on this
	    server: Check this box to use filters when you visit the
	    Inbox for this account.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
	  <term>If you chose IMAP:</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
         <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Checking for new mail: If you would like
	    Evolution to check for new mail
	    automatically, check the box and select a frequency in
	    minutes.  
            </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>If you want Evolution
	    to check for new messages in <emphasis>all</emphasis> your
	    IMAP folders, make sure the <guilabel>Check for new
	    messages in all folders</guilabel> box is selected.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Show only subscribed folders: Check this box if you
	    have more folders in your IMAP view than you want to
	    read.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              Override server-supplied namespace: If you like, enter a
              specific directory where your server stores mail for
              you.  Typical values are "mail" and "Mail."  For more
              information about how to use IMAP mail, see <xref
              linkend="usage-mail-subscriptions"/>.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Apply filters to new messages in INBOX on this
	    server: If you'd like your filters to work on this account
	    as well as on locally downloaded mail, check this box.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
     </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>

         <note id="imap-namespace">
            <title>What's an IMAP Namespace?</title>
                <para>
                    For IMAP mail servers, your sysadmin may provide
		    you with a specific namespace, the directory on
		    where your server stores mail for you. If you
		    check your IMAP mail and your folder list includes
		    files that don't look like mail folders, you
		    probably need to change your mail
		    namespace. Typical values are "mail" and "Mail."
		    If you prefer, you can choose to subscribe to
		    individual mail folders one at a time. For more
		    information about how to use IMAP mail, see <xref
		    linkend="usage-mail-subscriptions"/>.
               </para>
             </note>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="third-step">
      <title>Sending Email</title>
      <para>
	The <guilabel>Sending Email</guilabel> step lets you configure sending 
	email.
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Server Type: There are numerous server types that
	      Novell Evolution supports for sending your
	      mail.
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    SMTP: Sends mail using an outbound mail
                    server. This is the most common choice for sending
                    mail.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>Microsoft Exchange: Sends mail through a Microsoft
		    Exchange server using the Microsoft Exchange 2000
		    protocol. Available only if you have are using the
		    Novell Connector for Microsoft Exchange, which is installed
		    separately.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Groupwise: Sends mail through your GroupWise server. 
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Sendmail: Uses the Sendmail program to send mail
		    from your system. Sendmail is more flexible, but
		    is not as easy to configure, so you should only
		    select this option if you know how to set up a
		    Sendmail service.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        If you choose SMTP, there are a few additional items to enter:
        <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Host: enter your mail sending server's name or IP
              address here.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Server requires authentication: If your server
	      requires you to enter a password to send mail, check
	      this box.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Authentication Type: Unless you've been told otherwise,
	      your best bet is to leave this set at
	      <guilabel>Password</guilabel>.  If you're not sure, ask
	      your system administrator or ISP, or have
	      Novell Evolution check for
	      you by clicking <guilabel>Check for supported
	      types</guilabel>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Username: The account name you use when you login to
	      check your email.  Normally, this is the part of your
	      email address before the '@' character. For Exchange
	      servers, it is the username you would use to log in to a
	      Windows workstation at your company.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Remember Password: If you prefer to not enter
	      your password every time you check email, press this
	      button.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="step-three-b">
      <title>Account Management</title>
      <para>
        This is a very short section. You can pick two things: the
        name for the account, and whether it is the default account.
      </para>
      <para>
        The name you choose for the account is used for display within
        Evolution, and is not sent with any emails.  The suggested
        name is your email address, but you can use other words or
        phrases, like "Work," "Personal" or "First Account" if you
        like.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you check the box next to the label <guilabel>Make this my
      default account</guilabel>, Evolution will assume that you will
      send messages from this most often, and will set the
      "From" selector to this account whenever you open a new
      message. Only one account can be the default.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you have not done so already, you may also be asked to choose
      a time zone.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="fourth-step">
      <title>Importing Mail (Optional)</title>
      <para>
	If Novell Evolution finds mail or
	address files from another application, it will offer to
	import them.  If you're not sure which file format your mail
	program uses, ask your system administrator.  If you want, you
	can skip this step and return to it at a later time by
	selecting
	<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Import</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para>
	Novell Evolution can import the following types of
	files:
          <variablelist>
           <varlistentry>
	    <term>VCard (.vcf, .gcrd):</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>The contact format used by the GNOME, KDE, and
	         many other contact management applications. You
	         should be able to export to VCard format from any
                 address book or contact application. Failing that, export to CSV
                format and use the <command>csv2vcard</command>
              utility before importing.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Microsoft Outlook Express 4 (.mbx):</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
                Email file format used by Microsoft
                <application>Outlook Express 4</application>. For
                other versions of Microsoft Outlook and Outlook
                Express, see the workaround described in the note
                below.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>MBox (mbox):</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	       The email box format used by Mozilla, Netscape,
	       Novell Evolution, Eudora, and many other email clients.
  	     </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
       </variablelist>
</para>
<para>
    <note>
      <title>Microsoft Outlook and Outlook Express Users</title>
      <para>
        <application>Microsoft Outlook</application>, and versions of
        <application>Outlook Express</application> after
	version 4, use proprietary formats that Novell
	Evolution cannot read or import.  For contacts,
	you may have to email them to yourself and import them that
	way.  For email, see the instructions in <xref
	      linkend="outlook-migration-mail" />
    </para>
  </note>

    <note>
      <title>Netscape Users</title>
      <para>
	Before importing mail from Netscape, make sure you select
	<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Compact All
	Folders</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. If you don't,
	Novell Evolution will import and undelete
	the messages in your Trash folders.
      </para>
    </note>     
    <tip>
      <title>Exporting Files From Novell Evolution</title>
      <para>
        Novell Evolution uses standard file types for all its information,
        so you should have no trouble taking your information
          elsewhere if you want.
        </para>
	<para>
          For mail, that's <filename>mbox</filename>, for the calendar,
          <filename>iCal</filename>, and for the contacts, a database that
	    exports to vCards.
        </para>
      </tip>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

  <sect1 id="importing-mail-from-clients">
    <title>Importing Mail from Other Mail Clients</title>
    <para>
      Chances are, you already have your email in another mail program
      and don't want to lose the information.  The following section
      describes how to import mail from specific mail clients.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="mutt">
      <title>Importing Mail from mutt</title>
      <para>
	<application>mutt</application> is a text-based mail client
	which is shipped with many Linux and Unix distributions.
	<application>mutt</application> uses the standard mbox,
	maildir, and MH file formats, which makes importing your mail
	into Evolution relatively simple.  By default,
	<application>mutt</application> uses the mbox file format.
	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Open Novell Evolution
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click
	      <menuchoice>
		<guimenu>File</guimenu>
		<guimenuitem>Import</guimenuitem>
	      </menuchoice>
	      or press
	      <keycombo action="simul">
		<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
		<keycap>I</keycap>
	      </keycombo>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click <guilabel>Next</guilabel>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Select <guilabel>Import a Single File</guilabel>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click <guilabel>Browse</guilabel> and select the file
	      you would like to import from.  By default, your email
	      is stored in <filename>~/mbox</filename> for the mbox
	      format and <filename
	      class="directory">~/Maildir</filename> for the Maildir format.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      When prompted for what folder in
	      Evolution to import to,
	      select a folder.  You can also create a new folder and
	      drop it in there.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="kmail">
      <title>Importing Mail from KMail</title>
      <para>
        <application>KMail</application>
 is the mail client which is shipped with the KDE desktop
        environment.  <application>KMail</application> uses the
standard mbox file format, which
	means that importing your mail into
	Evolution is easy.
	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Open Novell Evolution
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click
	      <menuchoice>
		<guimenu>File</guimenu>
		<guimenuitem>Import</guimenuitem>
	      </menuchoice>
	      or press
	      <keycombo action="simul">
		<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
		<keycap>I</keycap>
	      </keycombo>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click <guilabel>Next</guilabel>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Select <guilabel>Import a Single File</guilabel>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click <guilabel>Browse</guilabel> and select the file
	      you would like to import from.  By default, KMail stores
	      its information in the Mail directory of your home
	      directory.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      When prompted for what folder in
	      Evolution to import to,
	      select a folder.  You can also create a new folder and
	      drop it in there.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="ui-intro">
    <title>What's What in Novell Evolution</title>
    <para>
        Now that you've gotten the first-run configuration out of the
        way, you're ready to get down to work.  Here's a quick
        explanation of what's going on in your main
        Novell Evolution window.
    </para>

    <figure id="preface-basic-interface">
      <title>The Novell Evolution Main Window</title>
      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Inbox</screeninfo>
	  <mediaobject>
             <imageobject>
                 <imagedata fileref="figures/mainwindow-pic" format="PNG" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/> 
             </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata  fileref="figures/full-1" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
      <guilabel>Menu Bar</guilabel>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <guilabel>menu bar</guilabel> gives you access to nearly all
      the features that can be found in Novell
      Evolution.
    </para>

    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-2" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
      <guilabel>Toolbar</guilabel>
    </para>

    <para>
      The <guilabel>Toolbar</guilabel> gives you fast and easy access to the
      most used features in each component.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-3" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
      <guilabel>Shortcut Bar</guilabel>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <guilabel>Shortcut Bar</guilabel> lets you switch between
    folders and between Evolution tools.  At the bottom of the
    shortcut bar there are buttons that let you switch tools, and 
    above that, all the available folders for the current tool. If you have the
      Evolution Connector for Microsoft Exchange installed, you will have an
      <guilabel>Exchange</guilabel> button in addition to buttons for the other tools.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-4" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
      <guilabel>Status Bar</guilabel>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Periodically, Novell Evolution will need to quietly
      display a message, or tell you the progress of a task.  This most
      often happens when you're checking or sending email.  These progress
    queues are shown here, in the <guilabel>Status Bar</guilabel>.
    The Online/Offline indicator is here, too, in the lower left of the window.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-5" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
      <guilabel>Search Tool</guilabel>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <guilabel>Search Tool</guilabel> lets you search through your email
      with precision so you can easily find what you're looking for.
    </para>

  <sect2 id="usage-mainwindow-shortcutbar">
    <title>The Shortcut Bar</title>
    <para>
        Novell Evolution's most important job is
        to give you access to your information and help you use it
        quickly.  One way it does that is through the
        shortcut bar, the column on the left
        hand side of the main window.  The  buttons with names
        like <guilabel>Mail</guilabel> and
        <guilabel>Contacts</guilabel> are the shortcuts. Above them
        is a list of folders for the current Evolution tool.
    </para>
    <para>
      The folder list organizes your mail, calendars, contact lists,
      and task lists in a tree, similar to a <glossterm linkend="filetree">file
      tree</glossterm>.  Most people will find one to four 
      folders at the base of the tree, depending on the tool and their
    system configuration. Each Evolution tool will have at least one,
    called <guilabel>On This Computer</guilabel>, for local
    information. For example, the folder list for the email tool will show any
    remote mail storage you have set up, plus local folders and 
    <guilabel>vFolders</guilabel>, or virtual folders, discussed in <xref
    linkend="usage-mail-organize-vfolders"/>. 
    </para>

    <para>
       If you get large volumes of mail, you'll want more folders than
       just your Inbox; you can also create multiple calendar, task,
      or contacts folders. 
    </para>
    <para>
      To create a new folder:
	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              Right click on the list of folders, and select 
              <guilabel>New Folder</guilabel>.
                <!--  FIXME: this was taken out: or press the keyboard shortcut  
                <keycombo action="simul">
		<keycap>Shift</keycap>
		<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
		<keycap>F</keycap>
	      </keycombo>.  -->
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Enter the name of the folder in the <guilabel>Folder
		Name</guilabel> field.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	 
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Choose the location of the new folder.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>

    <sect3 id="subfolders">
    <title>Subfolders</title>
      <para>
        Novell Evolution lets you nest folders
	inside of each other, so that you can have a detailed
	organizational system.
      </para>

    <para>
      Right-clicking will bring up a menu for just about anything in
      Novell Evolution.  If you right-click on a
      folder, you'll have a menu with the following options:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem>, to copy the folder to another place. When you select this item, Evolution offers a choice of locations to copy to. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Move</guimenuitem>, to move the folder to another location. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>, to delete the folder and all its contents. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>New Folder</guimenuitem>, to create another folder in the same location. </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><guimenuitem>Rename</guimenuitem>, to change its name. </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>, to delete the folder.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>, which lets you check the number of total and unread messages in a folder, and, for remote folders, lets you decide whether to copy the folder to your local system for offline operation.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      You can also rearrange folders and messages by dragging and
      dropping them.
    </para>

	<para>
	  Any time new mail arrives in a mail folder, that folder
	  label is displayed in bold text, along with the number of
	  new messages in that folder.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="usage-mainwindow-menubar">
    <title>The Menu Bar</title>
    <para>
      The menu bar's contents will always
      provide all the possible actions for any given view of your
      data.  If you're looking at your Inbox, most of the menu items
      will relate to mail; some will relate to other components of
      Novell Evolution and some, especially those
      in the <guimenu>File Menu</guimenu> will relate to the
      application as a whole. 
   </para> 
   <para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>File</guimenu>:</term>

          <listitem><para> Anything related to a file or to the
            operations of the application generally falls under this
            menu: creating things, saving them to disk, printing them,
            and quitting the program itself.  </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
              The <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu holds
              useful tools that help you edit text and move it around.
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>View</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
            This menu lets you decide how Novell Evolution 
            should look. Some of the features control the appearance of 
            Novell Evolution as a whole, and others 
            the way a particular kind of information appears.
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>Actions</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
	    Holds actions which maybe applied to a message.  Normally,
	    if there is only one target for the action &mdash; for
	    example, replying to a message &mdash; you can find it in
	    the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu.
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
             For all components of Evolution, you can access the
          settings and configuration options in the tools menu. You
          can also find things like filter settings and the Virtual
          Folder editor.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>Search</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
             Select menu items here to search for messages, or for
          phrases within a message. You can also see previous searches
          you have made.  In addition to the <guimenu>Search</guimenu>
          menu, there is a text entry box in the toolbar that you can
          use to search for messages.
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

       <varlistentry>
          <term> <guimenu>Help</guimenu>:</term>
          <listitem><para>
             Select among these items to open the
             Novell Evolution manual.
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
   </para>

   <para>
      Once you've familiarized yourself with the main
      window you can start doing things with it.  We'll
      start with the <guilabel>Summary</guilabel>, which provides a
      quick overview of your Novell
      Evolution information.
    </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="basics-mail">
      <title>Introducing Email</title>
      <para>
         Novell Evolution email is like other
         email programs in several ways:
     <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              It can sort and organize your mail in a wide variety of
              ways with folders, searches, and filters.
           </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              It can send and receive mail in HTML or as plain text,
              and makes it easy to send and receive multiple file
              attachments.
           </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
              It supports multiple mail sources, including <glossterm
              linkend="imap">IMAP</glossterm>, <glossterm
              linkend="pop">POP3</glossterm>, and local
              <filename>mbox</filename> or <filename>mh</filename>
              spools and files created by other mail programs.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      It lets you guard your privacy with encryption.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        However, Novell Evolution has some
        important differences.  First, it's built to handle very large
      amounts of mail.  The <link
      linkend="usage-mail-organize-spam">junk mail</link>, message <link
        linkend="usage-mail-organize-filters">filtering</link> and
        <link linkend="usage-mail-organize-search">searching</link>
        functions were built for speed and efficiency on large volumes
        of mail. There's also the <link
linkend="usage-mail-organize-vfolders">vFolder</link>, an advanced
        organizational feature not found in mainstream mail clients.
        If you get a lot of mail, or if you keep every message you get
        in case you need to refer to it later, you'll find this
        feature especially useful.
     </para>
     <para>
        Here's what the mailer looks like:

 <!-- ==============Figure=================================== -->

      <figure id="usage-mail-intro-fig">
          <title>Novell Evolution Mail</title>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Inbox</screeninfo>
            <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/mail-inbox" format="PNG" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/>
        </imageobject></mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
<!-- ==============End of Figure============================== -->
</para>
      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-1"
        format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Message List</guilabel>
      </para>
    
      <para>
        The <guilabel>Message List</guilabel> displays all the emails
        that you have.  This includes all your read, unread, and email
        that is flagged to be deleted.
      </para>

      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-2"
        format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Email
        Viewer</guilabel>
      </para>
    
      <para>
        This is where your email is displayed.
      </para>

      <para>
     If you find the view pane too small, you can resize
        the pane, enlarge the whole window, or double-click on the
        message in the message list to have it
        open in a new window.  To change the sizes of a pane, just click
        and hold on the divider between the two panes.  Then you can drag
        up and down to select the size of the panes.

    </para>
    <para> Just like with folders, you can right-click on messages in the
        message list and get a menu of possible actions: you can move,
        delete, or undelete them, and create filters or vFolders based
        on them.
      </para>
      <para>
        Most of the mail-related actions you'll want to perform are
        listed in the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu in the menu bar.
        The most frequently used ones, like
        <guimenuitem>Reply</guimenuitem> and
        <guimenuitem>Forward</guimenuitem>, also appear as buttons in
        the toolbar. Almost all of them are also located in the
        right-click menu and as keyboard shortcuts, which tend to be
        faster once you get the hang of them.  You can choose
        whichever way you like best; the idea is that the software
        should work the way you want, rather than making you work the
        way the it does.
      </para>

       <para>
         For an in-depth guide to the email capabilities of Novell
         Evolution, read <xref linkend="usage-mail"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="basics-calendar">
      <title>Introducing the Calendar</title>
      <para>
       To begin using the calendar, click the 
       <guilabel>Calendar</guilabel> button in the shortcut
       bar.  By default, the calendar starts showing
       today's schedule on a ruled background.  At the upper right,
       there's a monthly calendar you can use to switch days.  Below
       that, there's a <guilabel>Task</guilabel> pad, where you can
       keep a list of tasks separate from your calendar appointments.
       The day view in the calendar looks like this:

   <!-- ============== Figure ============================= -->
    <figure id="usage-calendar-fig">
      <title>Novell Evolution Calendar View</title>
      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Novell Evolution Contact Manager Window</screeninfo>
	<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/calendar" format="PNG" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/>
	</imageobject></mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  <!-- ============== End of Figure ============================= --> 

    </para>

      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-1"
        format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Appointment
        List</guilabel>
      </para>
  
      <para>
	The appointment list displays all your scheduled appointments.
      </para>

      <para>
	<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-2" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
	<guilabel>Task List</guilabel>
      </para>

      <para>
        Tasks are distinct from appointments in that they generally
        don't have times associated with them. You can see a larger
        view of your task list by clicking the
        <guilabel>Tasks</guilabel> button in the shortcut bar.
      </para>

      <para>
	<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-3" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
	<guilabel>Month Pane</guilabel>
      </para>

      <para>
	The month pane is a small view of a calendar month.
        To display additional months, drag the column border to
        the left. You can also select a range of days in the month
        pane to get a custom range of days displayed in the
        appointment list.
      </para>

      <para>
          For more information about the calendar
          read <xref linkend="usage-calendar"/>.
      </para>

    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="basics-contacts">
      <title>Introducing the Contacts Tool</title>
      <para>
        The Novell Evolution contacts tool
        can handle all of the functions of an address book, phone
        book, or Rolodex.  Of course, it's a lot easier to update
        Evolution than it is to change an actual paper book. Novell
        Evolution also allows easy synchronization with
        hand-held devices and functions with <glossterm
        linkend="ldap">LDAP</glossterm> directories on a network.
      </para>
      <para>
        Another advantage of the Novell Evolution
        contacts tool is its integration with the rest of the
        application.  For example, you can right-click on an email
        address in Evolution mail to create a contact entry instantly.
      </para>
      <para>
        To use the contacts tool, click the
        <guilabel>Contacts</guilabel> button in the shortcut bar.  <xref
        linkend="usage-contact-fig"/> shows the address book in all its
        organizational glory.  By default, the display shows all
        your contacts in alphabetical order, in a <glossterm
        linkend="minicard">minicard</glossterm> view.  You can select
        other views from the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu, and adjust
        the width of the columns by clicking and dragging the gray
        column dividers.
      </para>
      <para>
        The contacts tool looks like this:

      <figure id="usage-contact-fig">
	<title>Novell Evolution Contact Interface</title>
	<screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Novell Evolution Contact List Window</screeninfo>
	  <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/contact" format="PNG" srccredit="Kevin Breit"/>
  	  </imageobject></mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>
     </para>
      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-1"
        format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> <guilabel>Contact
        List</guilabel>
      </para>

      <para>
        The largest section of the contacts display shows a list of individual
        contacts. You can also search through the contacts in the same way
        that you search email folders, with the search tool on the
        right side of the toolbar.
      </para>

      <para>
	<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata  fileref="figures/full-2" format="PNG"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
	<guilabel>Alphanumeric Shortcuts</guilabel>
      </para>
      <para>
        Click one of the buttons along the right side of the
        window to view contacts that begin with the letter or number
        you click.
      </para>


      <para>
          For detailed instructions on how to use the address book,
          read <xref linkend="usage-contact"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>