<chapter id="usage-print">
  <title>Printing with Evolution</title>
  <para>
    If you've printed from most any other
    Gnome application, you should be able
    to print from Evolution without much
    trouble.
  </para>
  <para>
    Whether you're printing a message, a calendar page, or a selection
    of address cards, you can choose to print directly to a printer,
    or save the print output to a <glossterm
    linkend="postscript">postscript</glossterm> file.  You can also
    use the preview feature to see how your printed output will look.
  </para>
  
  <sect1 id="printpreview">
    <title>Print Preview</title>
    <para>
      <guilabel>Print Preview</guilabel> appears both as a button in
      the printing dialog and as an item in the
      <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu.  In both places, it does the same
      thing: it opens a new window that shows you what would happen if
      you were to print the current message, calendar, appointment, or
      address card.
    </para>
    <para>
      That window allows you to select which pages you want to see,
      and how close you'd like to look at them.  Zoom in or out, fit
      the page to the window (the <guilabel>Fit</guilabel> button)
      or match the width of the page and the window (the
      <guilabel>Fit Width</guilabel> button).  None of these buttons
      changes the way the page will be printed, but they do let you
      get a better look.  If you're satisfied with the way the your paper
      looks, click <guilabel>Print</guilabel> to send your document
      on its way.  If you'd like to change it, just close the
      <guilabel>Print Preview</guilabel> window and make the changes
      you want from your mail, calendar, or address book.
    </para>


 <!-- ==============Figure=================================== -->
 
      <figure id="print-preview">
	  <title>Print Preview</title>
	  <screenshot>
	    <screeninfo>Print Preview</screeninfo>
	    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/print-preview" format="PNG" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/>
	</imageobject></mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>
<!-- ==============End of Figure============================== -->

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="print-destination">
    <title>File or Printer?</title>
    <para>
       The printer selection window, shown in <xref
       linkend="print-dest"/>, lets you choose the format for
       printing&mdash; <guilabel>Generic Postscript</guilabel>,
       whether to write to a PDF file, and whether to print to a file
       or to an actual printer in Generic Postscript.  If you choose a
       printer, you'll be asked for the printer command (probably
       <command>lpr</command>) which your system uses.  If you
       choose to print to a file, you'll need to decide upon a
       filename.  And of course, you'll want to choose a number of
       copies, and whether to collate them.

	<note id="windows-ps">
	  <title>Printing to PostScript?</title>
	  <para>
           PostScript is the file format used by most laser printers,
           and in UNIX world is the easiest way to print to a file.
           However, most systems running Microsoft Windows can't
           recognize or handle PostScript files.  You'll need to print
           to PDF if you want to share your file with Windows users.
	  </para>
	</note>
    </para>

 <!-- ==============Figure=================================== -->
 
      <figure id="print-dest">
	  <title>Choosing a Printer</title>
	  <screenshot>
	    <screeninfo>Choosing a Printer</screeninfo>
	    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/print-dest" format="PNG" srccredit="Aaron Weber"/>
	</imageobject></mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </figure>
<!-- ==============End of Figure============================== -->

   <para>
     If you're printing a message that's more than one page, you'll
     have the option of choosing which pages to print.  If you're
     printing a calendar entry, you can decide what range of dates to
     print.  And, if you're printing contact cards, you can decide
     whether to print only the selected cards, or all of them.
   </para>
    <para>
      When you're ready, click <guilabel>Print</guilabel> to print,
      <guilabel>Preview</guilabel> to have a look (or another look)
      at the preview, or <guilabel>Cancel</guilabel> to cancel the
      whole deal.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>







